<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature on </title>
    <link>/tags/literature/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Literature on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/literature/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>SVs</title>
      <link>/2020/12/16/svs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/16/svs/</guid>
      <description>Association of Structural Variation with Cardiometabolic Traits in Finns bioRxiv from Ira Hall’s group.
From the intro:
 Targeted analysis of known SVs across large cohorts associated HP and LPA with cholesterol levels  This study:
 &amp;gt;20x WGS SV calling  svtools: discovery with LUMPY, CNVnator, svtyper; then genotyping. GenomeSTRiP and CNVnator for cohort-level CNVs. 55k DEL, 32k DUP, 187 INV, 3k MEI, 34k mCNV (, 4k BND).  ~130K SVs across 4-5K Finnish individuals 35% overlap with 1KG and gnomAD Advantage of the Finnish population: some rare variants enriched due to bottlenecks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Japanese reference genome, inversion GWAS, deCODE SVs</title>
      <link>/2019/12/08/japanese-reference-genome-inversion-gwas-decode-svs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/08/japanese-reference-genome-inversion-gwas-decode-svs/</guid>
      <description>JG1 Japanese reference genome from 3 de novo assemblies Takayama et al. (2019) sequenced 3 Japanese individuals using high depth PacBio, Bionano and short read sequencing to create a better reference genome for the Japanese population, JG1. They made a meta-assembly, merging the 3 de novo assemblies and, when possible, picked the major allele across the 3 individuals. They show that JG1 reduces the number of variants, including the number of false positives, while still detecting important disease-causing SNVs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1PE - Week 1(-2)</title>
      <link>/2019/06/17/1pe-week-1-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/17/1pe-week-1-2/</guid>
      <description>I’m going to try reading one paper everyday (1PE). This is week 1 (and 2 because I failed pretty quickly…).
A robust benchmark for germline structural variant detection bioRxiv 2019
This is the preprint describing the effort by the Genome in a Bottle consortium to produce a SV gold standard on HG002. They used a lot of SV callers and different technologies on HG002 and his parents.
 Their tier 1 set contains ~10K SVs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minimizers, CNV burden, and ref-guided scaffolding</title>
      <link>/2019/02/12/minimizers-cnv-burden-and-ref-guided-scaffolding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/12/minimizers-cnv-burden-and-ref-guided-scaffolding/</guid>
      <description>I accumulated a huge number of articles in Feedly and I don’t know what to do about them. One thing I decided to try was to go over them quickly and write down what I want to remember. I don’t think I will read these kind of posts again but maybe it will help me remember or eventually find the reference again.
Minimizer indexes I would like to understand better minimizer indexes as they seem to be more and more important in the field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cool tools, &#39;machine-learning&#39;, and a population-specific reference genome</title>
      <link>/2018/07/22/cool-tools-machine-learning-and-a-population-specific-reference-genome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/22/cool-tools-machine-learning-and-a-population-specific-reference-genome/</guid>
      <description>I accumulated a huge number of articles in Feedly and I don’t know what to do about them. One thing I decided to try was to go over them quickly and write down what I want to remember. I don’t think I will read these kind of posts again but maybe it will help me remember or eventually find the reference again.
genomeview - an extensible python-based genomics visualization engine (bioRxiv, docs).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SV-eQTLs in GTEx data from WGS</title>
      <link>/2018/03/31/chiang-sveqtl-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/31/chiang-sveqtl-2017/</guid>
      <description>This is a review of “The impact of structural variation on human gene expression” (Chiang Nat Gen 2017) from the Hall lab.
Summary Using deep WGS from 147 individuals in GTEx they called SVs and eQTLs across 13 tissues (RNA-seq). For the first time they could investigate the contribution of small SVs in gene expression changes, comparing it with SNVs and indels. They estimated that 3.5-6.8% of eQTLs are caused by SVs and that SVs tend to have a larger effect size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lit Digest - Testing overlap between genomic regions</title>
      <link>/2017/10/19/lit-digest-testing-overlap-between-genomic-regions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/19/lit-digest-testing-overlap-between-genomic-regions/</guid>
      <description>LOLA: enrichment analysis for genomic region sets and regulatory elements in R and Bioconductor Sheffield 2015
 Expanding on the gene-centric enrichment analyses. The R package efficiently tests for significant overlap (Fisher test) and report results. The user specify the universe, i.e. all the regions that could have been selected. To test enrichment in differential-like analysis where a subset of regions is tested for overlap. Not directly feasible for CNVs expect if we provide a set of control regions as universe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epilepsy genes candidates</title>
      <link>/2017/10/02/epilepsy-genes-candidates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/02/epilepsy-genes-candidates/</guid>
      <description>We had a few candidate genes that could be affected by non-coding CNVs. We could try to recreate the deletions using CRISPR but we need to know the cell type to phenotype (and how/what to phenotype). I’ll try to find information from the various databases and from publication.
Our collaborators can differentiate cells into glutamatergic neurons (as opposed to GABA-ergic). For the phenotype, we could monitor the gene expression levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome graphs</title>
      <link>/2017/09/23/genome-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/23/genome-graphs/</guid>
      <description>Why genome graphs ?  Better genome reference.  Higher mapping rate in the presence of variation. Less “biased” toward the fixed linear European reference genome. Easier to update. No more major version.  Better annotation for non-SNV variants.  More general and intuitive. Only one way to place indels. Complex variants involving several canonical types.  Improved variant calling.  Integrating known variants. Would be useful for SVs with breakpoint resolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lit Digest - Non-coding variants in regulatory regions</title>
      <link>/2017/09/22/lit-digest-non-coding-variants-in-regulatory-regions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/22/lit-digest-non-coding-variants-in-regulatory-regions/</guid>
      <description>Genome-wide analysis of noncoding regulatory mutations in cancer Weinhold &amp;amp; Jacobsen et al., Nature Genetics 2014
 863 tumors from TCGA and co. Identify recurrent non-coding variants in cancer. PLEKHS1, WDR74, SDHD had such variants in upstream regulatory elements.  Promoter/enhancer have similar rate of somatic mutation as transcribed regions (~3 per Mb), and lower than intergenic (~6 per Mb), supporting the presence of functional variants.
They used three approaches to identify functional ncSNV candidates:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lit Digest - SV and long-read sequencing</title>
      <link>/2017/09/20/lit-digest-sv-and-long-read-sequencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/20/lit-digest-sv-and-long-read-sequencing/</guid>
      <description>How many more SVs ? Which types of SVs ?  Identifying structural variants using linked-read sequencing data Elyanow, biorXiv 2017
 Better than other methods…   Mapping And Phasing Of Structural Variation In Patient Genomes Using Nanopore Sequencing Stancu, bioRxiv 2017
 2 patients with congenital abnormalities, with MinION (11x/16x). Better at finding complex chromothripsis. 3K novel SVs, majority being duplication &amp;lt;200 bp. Phasing showed the de novo chromothripsis occurred in paternal chromosomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misc</title>
      <link>/2017/08/20/misc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/20/misc/</guid>
      <description>Misc Cancer, chromatin loop and SVs Chromatin loop anchor points (LAPs) as sites of regulatory importance but also genomic fragility. They harbour an excess of SV breakpoints in cancers, are prone to double strand breaks in somatic cells, and are bound by DNA repair complex proteins.
Kaiser &amp;amp; Semple bioRxiv 2017
 TE suppression in cancer TE suppression proposed as a mechanism for immune escape in acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) and myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing the quality of an assembly</title>
      <link>/2017/08/10/testing-the-quality-of-an-assembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/10/testing-the-quality-of-an-assembly/</guid>
      <description>Mapping reads Coverage analysis Regions with unusual coverage might be mis-assembled (Nagarajan &amp;amp; Pop).
Coverage is too high -&amp;gt; collapse of a repeat. Coverage is too low -&amp;gt; incorrect join.
 Calling SNPs  An excess of SNPs might be a sign of mis-assemblies. If assembling an haploid genome, there should not be any SNPs.  In Steinberg et al, ~80K SNVs were found when aligning reads to their haploid assembly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single Cell RNA-seq and GBM</title>
      <link>/2017/05/23/single-cell-rna-seq-and-gbm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/23/single-cell-rna-seq-and-gbm/</guid>
      <description>Three studies used single cell RNA-seq on brain cancer tumors. They also called large CNA from this data. How ?
scRNA highlights intra-tumoral heterogeneity in primary glioblastoma Patel et al. (Science 2014)
 Intra-tumoral heterogeneity is thought to be an important factor of treatment resistance and relapses. GBM is one of the most lethal human malignancy.  They show that known suptype classifier for GBMs are actually expressed differently across the cells from the same tumor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Family-based designs for gene-association studies</title>
      <link>/2017/04/09/family-based-designs-for-gene-association-studies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/09/family-based-designs-for-gene-association-studies/</guid>
      <description>Different type of family information can be used. Trio designs (affected offspring plus parents) seems to have the most power but having both affected and unaffected siblings is useful too.
A positive result in a family-based test means there is both linkage and association. It avoids problems with population stratification or admixture.
Transmission Disequilibrium Test (TDT) The TDT compares the number of observed allele transmitted to the affected offspring with the expected number following Mendelian transmission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epilepsy</title>
      <link>/2017/04/02/epilepsy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/02/epilepsy/</guid>
      <description>Duplication hotspots, rare genomic disorders, and common disease by Mefford et al, Current Opinion in Genetics and Development 2009.
Segmental duplications sensitize ~10% of the genome to recurrent microdeletions and microduplications. Mefford et al review the association of these recurrent events with diseases. A subset of these hotspots plays an important role in austism, schizphrenia, and epilepsy. In general, the hotspots are characterized by a stretch of unique sequence (50 kb-10 Mb) flanked by large (&amp;gt;10 kb), highly homologous (&amp;gt;95%) segmental duplications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsatellite Instability</title>
      <link>/2017/02/05/microsatellite-instability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/02/05/microsatellite-instability/</guid>
      <description>Microsatellites are a type of STRs with repeat units of 1-6 bp. Microsatellite instability is an indicator of larger genome instability and an important prognostic factor in several cancers (e.g. colorectal). MSI is actually a marker of favorable prognosis. It’s a form of hypermutation caused by defective DNA mismatch repair (MMR). For example, through inactivation of MLH1, MSH2 or MSH3 genes. For this reason, MSI is also characterized by high rates of single-nucleotide-substitution (SNS) mutations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Self-Assessment Trap</title>
      <link>/2017/01/14/the-self-assessment-trap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/14/the-self-assessment-trap/</guid>
      <description>I just read a short correspondence about the self-assessment trap, i.e. when the author is the judge, jury and executioner of comparing his method against existing methods. One visible outcome is that most methods are found to be the best, which is unlikely to be true.
A typical explanation for this bias is the selection by the authors of just the metrics in which their method is better. Different aspects of the same problem are emphasized in different papers and used for benchmarking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lit Digest - SVs and TEs</title>
      <link>/2017/01/10/lit-digest-svs-and-tes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/10/lit-digest-svs-and-tes/</guid>
      <description>CrowdVariant: a crowdsourcing approach to classify copy number variants bioRxiv
There is no good gold-standard dataset for small CNVs (&amp;lt;10 kb). CrowdVariant is a crowdsourcing framework that aim at identifying high quality CNV calls in NA24385, an Ashkenazim reference sample from Genome In A Bottle Consortium.
They show that even annotations from non-expert helps assigning copy number status from putative calls. They then provide 1 781 of such high confidence CNVs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local assembly</title>
      <link>/2016/08/17/local-assembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/17/local-assembly/</guid>
      <description>TIGRA: A targeted iterative graph routing assembler for breakpoint assembly by Ken Chen et al, Genome Research 2014.
Targeted Iterative Graph Routing Assembler was widely used in large-scale projects (e.g. 1KGP) for breakpoints assembly of deletions and mobile element insertion. It’s an old effort, that they started in 2008, which was optimized and improved across the years.
To clarify, TIGRA assembles the breakpoint region of SV, not the entire SV region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SV, gene expression, cancer types, Alu insertions.</title>
      <link>/2016/06/18/sv-gene-expression-cancer-types-alu-insertions./</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/06/18/sv-gene-expression-cancer-types-alu-insertions./</guid>
      <description>The impact of structural variation on human gene expression by Chiang et al, biorXiv 2016.
The group from Ira Hall and the GTEx consortium investigated how much SVs affect gene expression and put it in context with existing SNV eQTLs work. The jointly analyze the effect of SNVs, indels and SVs across 13 tissues in 147 individuals. Their main results are:
 SVs look like the causal variants of 3.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>