<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sv on </title>
    <link>/tags/sv/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sv on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/sv/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Comparing SV: Viola, SV clustering, MARS and TT-MARS</title>
      <link>/2022/04/30/litreviews-svsmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/04/30/litreviews-svsmethods/</guid>
      <description>Viola: a structural variant signature extractor with user-defined classifications Sugita et al Bioinformatics 2022
Website
Viola is a python package to merge SV calls and look for mutation signatures in cancer samples. It’s intended to be used within Python scripts.
The annotation (can) include:
 SV types/length Genes Fragile sites Replication timing Microhomology  The “categories” can be customized as the intersection of multiple simpler ones, e.g. “duplications larger than XXbp in fragile sites”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lit skimming: CNV in Brazilian cohort, epigenomic &amp; SVs in human and chimp</title>
      <link>/2021/03/03/lit-skimming-cnv-in-brazilian-cohort-epigenomic-svs-in-human-and-chimp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/03/03/lit-skimming-cnv-in-brazilian-cohort-epigenomic-svs-in-human-and-chimp/</guid>
      <description>Copy number variation (CNV) identification, interpretation, and database from Brazilian patients Genet Mol Biol. 2020
 adress lack of diversity in genomics study thanks to diverse/admixed Brazilian population. Methods  268 clinical samples, inc. neurodev disorders and/or congenital malformations. microarrays. SVs&amp;gt; 50 probes and &amp;gt;150-200 kbp annotation with DGV, DEVIPHER, ClinVar, ClinGen, RefSeq genes. ACMG guidelines pathogenic if not in DGV (&amp;gt;=3 individuals and &amp;gt;50% coverage) and: &amp;gt;3Mb; or known; or OMIM gene + DECIPHER/ClinVar/ClinGen + phenotype match  Results: more frequent CNVs in their dataset compared to open resources (which?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional SVs: GWAS, long-read for NDDs, disruption prediction</title>
      <link>/2021/02/24/functional-svs-gwas-long-read-for-ndds-disruption-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/02/24/functional-svs-gwas-long-read-for-ndds-disruption-prediction/</guid>
      <description>Association of Structural Variation with Cardiometabolic Traits in Finns bioRxiv Chen et al. (2020)
From the intro  Targeted analysis of known SVs across large cohorts associated HP and LPA with cholesterol levels   In this study  &amp;gt;20x WGS SV calling  svtools: discovery with LUMPY, CNVnator, svtyper; then genotyping. GenomeSTRiP and CNVnator for cohort-level CNVs. 55k DEL, 32k DUP, 187 INV, 3k MEI, 34k mCNV (, 4k BND).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
