<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jean Monlong</author>
    <rights>(C) 2019</rights>
    <updated>2019-12-08 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Japanese reference genome, inversion GWAS, deCODE SVs</title>
          <link>/2019/12/08/japanese-reference-genome-inversion-gwas-decode-svs/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2019/12/08/japanese-reference-genome-inversion-gwas-decode-svs/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;jg1-japanese-reference-genome-from-3-de-novo-assemblies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;JG1 Japanese reference genome from 3 de novo assemblies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Takayama et al. (&lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Takayama2019&#34; role=&#34;doc-biblioref&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; sequenced 3 Japanese individuals using high depth PacBio, Bionano and short read sequencing to create a better reference genome for the Japanese population, JG1.
They made a meta-assembly, merging the 3 de novo assemblies and, when possible, picked the major allele across the 3 individuals.
They show that JG1 reduces the number of variants, including the number of false positives, while still detecting important disease-causing SNVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They wanted to fix two problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rare variants in the reference genomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fact that Asian haplotypes are present in only 4.3% of the reference genome Asian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also used sequence-tagged site (STS) markers to place the contigs to chromosomes.
Those come from sequence and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiation_hybrid_mapping&#34;&gt;radiation hybrid maps&lt;/a&gt; (basically cut the chromosomes in pieces, separate them, test the presence of markers and approximate the distance between markers based on how often they co-occur).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asssembly facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Falcon assembler on ~120X PacBio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BioNano &amp;gt;150X&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pilon polished with ~55X Illumina reads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;N50: 86 Mbp, 60 Mbp, 58 Mbp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~3.1 Gbp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;85K STS markers to anchor contigs to chromosomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some manual steps to fix sex chromosomes, mitochondiral genome, or the gap lengths.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To modify their meta-assembly with the major allele they called SNVs and SVs using minimap2+paftools and created the final sequence using &lt;code&gt;bcftools consensus&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using HapMap samples, JG1 haplotypes cluster with Asian and Japanese individuals.
Many of the variants (relative to hg19) had allele frequency 1 in a cohort of 3.5K Japanese individuals.
This represent 98% of the “Japanese-fixed” variant found in this cohort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For SVs, they showed that the distribution was good and that the read coverage was “flatter” when using JG1.
I don’t really understand their coverage analysis.
It looks like they called SVs from short-reads using hg38 and JG1 but then it’s not clear which SVs were used to compared the coverage. Both? GRCh38 on JG1?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They provide the JG1 reference sequence and chain files for lift over &lt;a href=&#34;https://jmorp.megabank.tohoku.ac.jp/201911/downloads#sequence&#34;&gt;on their website&lt;/a&gt;.
They have also lifted over the GATK resource bundles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The made the chromosome drawing using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/tools/gdp&#34;&gt;NCBI Genome Decoration Page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To read from their reference list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dewey et al proposed a modified version of the reference genome that includes the major allele for different populations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;association-study-of-21-inversions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Association study of 21 inversions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;González et al. (&lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Gonzalez2019&#34; role=&#34;doc-biblioref&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; imputed the presence of inversions in &amp;gt;400K Europeans individuals (UK Biobank) and performed association tests against 25 obesity-related traits.
Seven inversions were associated with multiple diseases.
Some inversions could be disrupting TADs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the intro:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A common inversion in 8p23.1 has been linked to obesity, autism, neuroticism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inversion at 17q21.31 was associated with Alzheimer, Parkinson diseases, heart failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inversions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 spanned multiple genes: .45-4 Mbp flanked by SD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 intragenic from 0.7-5 Kbp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13 intergenic from 0.7-90 Kbp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The associations found in the UK Biobank were further validated in two other datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They found a case were both the non-inverted allele of 8p23.1 is also associated with different diseases (diabetes, hypertension, asthma).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many of the significant associations, none of the SNPs located within the inverted region were associated with the phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further investigate the functional effect of the inversions, they imputed the genotype of samples with expression data (GTEx).
They found significant differences in gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also compared the location of the inversions with tissue-specific genes and their TADs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They performed a mediation analysis and found that Obesity mediates the association with diabetes and hypertension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To read next:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giner-Delgado, C. et al. Evolutionary and functional impact of common polymorphic inversions in the human genome. Nat. Commun. 10, 4222 (2019).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;long-read-sequencing-of-1817-icelanders-to-analyze-structural-variation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Long-read sequencing of 1,817 Icelanders to analyze structural variation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Beyter et al. (&lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Beyter2019&#34; role=&#34;doc-biblioref&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; discovered SVs using long-read sequencing in almost 2K Icelanders and imputed their presence in 166K Icelanders from SNP arrays.
They performed association tests with the phenotype available and notably found a 14 Kbp deletion that overlaps the first exon of PCSK9 and correlates with lower LDL cholesterol levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,817 Icelanders, including 369 trios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14.7X ONT sequencing, N50 ~15 Kbp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SVs detected with Sniffles and refined with short-reads using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/smehringer/SViper&#34;&gt;SViper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validated using raw signal using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DecodeGenetics/nanopolish/tree/squigglesv&#34;&gt;SquiggleSVFilter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;median of 23K autosomal SVs per individual (~50/50 insertions/deletions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SV catalog:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;68K SVs after merging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;48K SVs as high-confidence, meaning that they could be imputed from SNP arrays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discoveries:
- Coding SVs are more rare.
- Large SVs are more rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They compared GWAS catalogs with their SVs and found 30 SVs impacting coding exons that are plausible causal variants.
They also performed a GWAS using phenotypes from their cohort and found a rare 14 Kbp deletion that overlaps the first exon of PCSK9 and correlates with lower LDL cholesterol levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SVs were merged based on the reciprocal overlap (using the strange insertion projection technique).
They built a graph with SVs as linked nodes if they overlap.
Treating the problem as a corrupted clique problem, they identified cliques to represent the minimum number of edge additions or removal.
The representative most frequent SV in term of site and size was picked for each clique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They performed association testing using BOLT-LMM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SV catalog will be available when the paper is published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;graphtyper2&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GraphTyper2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Eggertsson et al. (&lt;a href=&#34;#ref-Eggertsson2019&#34; role=&#34;doc-biblioref&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; improved their variant genotyper to integrate structural variants.
They show that it can genotype SNVs, indels and SVs from short-read data in large-scale datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used the syndip dataset, long-read sequencing and variant segregation in families to assess the quality of the predicted genotypes.
They genotyped 50K Icelanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach is very similar to BayesTyper: SVs are discovered with methods likes Manta, then genotyped.
Many of the input SVs might be errors but it’s not a big problem because the genotyper can figure out if the variant is supported or not by mapped reads.
It is incredible that BayesTyper was not mentioned in the paper (or cited).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deletions, insertions, inversions, duplications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add just the sequence around the breakpoint (up to 152 bp), not the full allele.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sliding window approach from a BAM file, now 1.2 Mbp long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syndip results: recall ~0.7/0.5 for DEL/INS; FDR ~0.2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;83 CPU hours per sample on average.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One limitation of this breakpoint-centric approach is that some informative reads might be discarded.
In practice it might not make a big difference.
I don’t know how many unique insertions &amp;gt;300 bp exists in the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They actually use two models to genotype SVs, one centered around the breakpoint alignment and the other on coverage.
The prediction with the highest genotype quality is returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Paragraph, they only compared the genotypes to methods that discover (sometimes then genotype) SVs.
When comparing to Delly then didn’t compare it on insertions although it can genotype insertions.
However their evaluation criterion was more stringent that what we use.
It’s based on the distance between the true and predicted breakpoints, using ~20 bp as a typical cut-off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They compared the performance while using only SVs discovered in short-reads or when including SVs found in long-read sequencing studies.
They found that the latter performs better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They merge the calls using their own tool, called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DecodeGenetics/svimmer&#34;&gt;svimmer&lt;/a&gt;, which keeps the information they want and only sites information.
SVs are grouped based on type, location (&amp;lt;200bp breakpoint diff), size (&amp;lt;100bp diff).
The most common SV in the group is picked as representative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They genotyped 500K SVs, including 80K high-confidence SVs.
I’m not sure what they mean by high-confidence.
Maybe it’s just a genotyping quality threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Beyter2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyter, Doruk, Helga Ingimundardottir, Hannes Eggertsson, Eythor Bjornsson,..., and Kari Stefansson. 2019. “Long Read Sequencing of 1,817 Icelanders Provides Insight into the Role of Structural Variants in Human Disease.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/848366&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/848366&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Eggertsson2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eggertsson, Hannes P., Snaedis Kristmundsdottir, Doruk Beyter, Hakon Jonsson,..., and Pall Melsted. 2019. “GraphTyper2 Enables Population-Scale Genotyping of Structural Variation Using Pangenome Graphs.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-13341-9&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-13341-9&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Gonzalez2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;González, Juan R, Carlos Ruiz-Arenas, Alejandro Cáceres, Ignasi Morán,..., and Luis A Pérez-Jurado. 2019. “Polymorphic Inversions Underlie the Shared Genetic Susceptibility to Prevalent Common Diseases.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/859280&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/859280&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Takayama2019&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Takayama, Jun, Shu Tadaka, Kenji Yano, Fumiki Katsuoka,..., and Gen Tamiya. 2019. “Construction and Integration of Three de Novo Japanese Human Genome Assemblies Toward a Population-Specific Reference.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/861658&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/861658&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>1PE - Week 1(-2)</title>
          <link>/2019/06/17/1pe-week-1-2/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2019/06/17/1pe-week-1-2/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try reading one paper everyday (1PE).
This is week 1 (and 2 because I failed pretty quickly…).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-robust-benchmark-for-germline-structural-variant-detection&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A robust benchmark for germline structural variant detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/664623v2&#34;&gt;bioRxiv 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the preprint describing the effort by the Genome in a Bottle consortium to produce a &lt;strong&gt;SV gold standard&lt;/strong&gt; on HG002.
They used a lot of SV callers and different technologies on HG002 and his parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their tier 1 set contains ~10K SVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They used a step-wise filtering pipeline to keep variants that
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have no duplicates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are supported by 2 technologies or 5 callers or BioNano support in trio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;were genotyped with enough support in HG002 by svviz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;were not complex (i.e. isolated).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;were located in region with confident diploid assembly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They found more large insertions in tandem repeats than large deletions. Is it because TRs are collapsed in the reference genome? Or just the general deletion bias of the reference?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The support for the alternate allele was around 50% for long reads but only ~30% for short reads, another good argument about the long reads lack of reference bias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comparison with additional long read datasets showed that some 5% of insertions might still be missing from their truth set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nhansen/SVanalyzer&#34;&gt;SVAnalyzer&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to cluster SVs from different caller while taking repeats into account&lt;/strong&gt;.
This new method compares haplotypes sequences of the variants and cluster SVs by proportion of divergent sequences.
That sounds very interesting and it has a &lt;em&gt;benchmark&lt;/em&gt; module to evaluate a call set vs a truth set (although they used something different for evaluation in this paper).
Clusters are defined as connected components in a network constructed with this similarity measure.
However it’s not clear how the SVs from the same cluster are merged.
From reviewing the Perl code it seems like the representative SV for a cluster is randomly selected from the largest subcluster of exactly matched variants (eventually randomly selected if multiple subcluster of maximal size).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variants were also evaluated and genotyped with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nspies/svviz2&#34;&gt;svviz2&lt;/a&gt; to keep variants with enough long reads supporting the alternate allele.
&lt;strong&gt;svviz2&lt;/strong&gt; is a new version of svviz that can not only visualize support for SVs but also evaluate and genotype SVs in an unsupervised manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spiralgenetics/truvari&#34;&gt;truvari&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to compare a test set with this truth set&lt;/strong&gt;.
Very similar to what we are doing with sveval but as before I find the criteria too lax.
The called variant needed to be within 30% of the true size and located at less than 2 kbp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future directions include producing similar dataset for GRCh38 and using better long-read sequencing (CCS PacBio and ultra-long nanopore).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;rmetl-sensitive-mobile-element-insertion-detection-with-long-read-realignment&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;rMETL: sensitive mobile element insertion detection with long read realignment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/bioinformatics/btz106/5317164&#34;&gt;Bioinformatics 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very short application note promoting a MEI caller from long-reads.
The language is unfortunately not always clear.
For that reason I didn’t completely grasp the methodology although several cartoons were provided in supplementary materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly, discordant reads are first extracted, more specifically the sequence that is discordant with the reference (and a few bps-long flanks), then clustered and aligned to the consensus sequence of known TE (L1, Alus, SVA).
From this realignment, ME insertions and deletions are genotyped following standard heuristics.
Their comparison with Sniffles shows that rMETL is more sensitive, especially at low coverage.
They used simulated and real data, using the 1KGP MEI catalog as gold standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The breakpoint fine-tuning step is a bit vague.&lt;/strong&gt;
In the supplements, they mention something about deriving the breakpoint from the alignment as the average of the breaks?
I think that it’s the trickiest part for MEI callers but also the most exciting feature that could be gained from long reads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side note, the acronym is pretty bad: a few cherry picked letters that make up a word that sounds like another existing MEI caller (MELT).
&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;ealignment-based &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;obile &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;lement insertion detection &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ool for &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;ong read, rMETL…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;statistical-tests-p-values-confidence-intervals-and-power-a-guide-to-misinterpretations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statistical tests, P values, confidence intervals, and power: a guide to misinterpretations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10654-016-0149-3&#34;&gt;European Journal of Epidemiology 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important point discussed is how we should study a question completely instead of focusing only on binary hypotheses (e.g. &lt;em&gt;is the difference significant?&lt;/em&gt;).
Both in teaching and application, the aim is wrongly about testing the null hypothesis.
But a study should &lt;strong&gt;not only report p-values but also effect size, confidence interval and exploration of the context in which the conclusions are valid&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more refined goal of statistical analysis is to provide an evaluation of certainty or uncertainty regarding the size of an effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ways that P-values might not be accurate.
A p-value test how well the data fits &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the assumptions of the null model, both statistical model and data generation.
It includes the parameter(s) of interest but also other assumptions about the model or test.
Even non-parametric methods depend on assumptions such as random sampling.
Methods such as sensitivity and bias analysis can investigate such problems.
It is important to keep in mind &lt;em&gt;hidden&lt;/em&gt; assumptions and challenge them as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statistical model is much more than an equation with Greek letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the assumption that the analysis was not performed only to test significance (&lt;strong&gt;analysis bias&lt;/strong&gt;) or that the results were not reported only based on their significance (&lt;strong&gt;reporting and publication bias&lt;/strong&gt;).
I understand the first one as trying out several tests/models until reaching significance.
The second might be testing several hypotheses and reporting only the ones that are significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They list misinterpretations that cover what the P-value means, what to conclude from them, how to combine them together (e.g. replication).
Same for confidence intervals and power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a bit annoyed by one type of misinterpretation that is more about the expression &lt;em&gt;“the chance that”&lt;/em&gt;.
They argue that the &lt;em&gt;chance of making an error&lt;/em&gt; is either 0% if you conclude right or 100% if not.
I understand it like the &lt;em&gt;probability of making an error from seeing our data&lt;/em&gt; but apparently you are either right or wrong and that’s it.
A bit annoying to repeat that several times over several misconceptions.
It felt like nitpicking. Maybe it’s important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end they quote Fisher who said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No scientific worker has a fixed level of significance at which from year to year, and in all circumstances, he rejects hypotheses; he rather gives his mind to each particular case in the light of his evidence and his ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Credible_interval&#34;&gt;Bayesian posterior/credible intervals&lt;/a&gt;, the Bayesian equivalent of confidence intervals (although different like P-values vs predictive posterior P-values).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;representing-and-decomposing-genomic-structural-variants-as-balanced-integer-flows-on-sequence-graphs&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Representing and decomposing genomic structural variants as balanced integer flows on sequence graphs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-016-1258-4&#34;&gt;BMC Bioinformatics 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a set of SV breakpoints, the approach described in this article can recreate the evolutionary history.
Briefly a &lt;strong&gt;sequence graph is first build&lt;/strong&gt; using breakpoint and copy number information, for example &lt;strong&gt;from short-read sequencing&lt;/strong&gt;.
The goal is then to &lt;strong&gt;find the history graph that best fit this sequence graph&lt;/strong&gt;.
A history graph is multi-layered, each layer representing a change in the original genome (top) due to a rearrangement.
Nodes contain sequences; edges represent either adjacency in the genome or the evolution of the sequence through layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I understand the goal of the method but I skipped all the math.
I was already failing my &lt;em&gt;1 Paper Everyday&lt;/em&gt; at this point and it seem too big of a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-presence-and-impact-of-reference-bias-on-population-genomic-studies-of-prehistoric-human-populations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The presence and impact of reference bias on population genomic studies of prehistoric human populations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/487983v2&#34;&gt;bioRxiv 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient DNA studies are more sensitive to reference bias&lt;/strong&gt; for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shorter reads because material degraded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;low coverage because of the small amount of material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some methods to deal with the data like the “pseudo-haploid” approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reference bias in variant calling can then impact frequency estimates and other population genetics analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure why one would like to use the &lt;strong&gt;“pseudo-haploid” approach&lt;/strong&gt;: picking one read randomly at each site to represent a haploid version of the SNP.
Maybe it makes downstream analysis easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing the mapping stringency is a bit of a quandary: too stringent and the reference bias is exacerbated; too lax and multi-mapping impacts variant calling later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the way the reference bias was tested was to modify reads with a reference nucleotide with the alternative allele.
Then both the real reads and modified reads were pooled together, making sure that 50% supported each allele.
They observed bias in all samples and apparently across the entire genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The larger the read the smaller the reference bias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The random sampling approach (“pseudo-haploid”) is more sensitive to reference bias than diploid calling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, &lt;strong&gt;the reference genome was also split into population of origin&lt;/strong&gt; (from a paper by Ed Green).
I had never seen this kind of partitioning before.
I should keep this in mind.
They found that segments of African origin were affected the least by reference bias and the opposite for European ancestry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors propose to filter reads to counter some potential reference bias.
Reads would be kept only if changing the nucleotide of interest didn’t change its mapping location.
The nucleotide of interest can be changed either in the read or the reference genome (using a third nucleotide than the ref/alt alleles).
This post-mapping correction helps but couldn’t correct the bias completely.
That would require an unbiased mapping step (genome graphs!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TIL of post-mortem deamination: deaminated nucleotides are then misread by DNA polymerase, looking like C-&amp;gt;T or G-&amp;gt;A mutations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;crisprcas9-mediated-scanning-for-regulatory-elements-required-for-hprt1-expression-via-thousands-of-large-programmed-genomic-deletions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CRISPR/Cas9-Mediated Scanning for Regulatory Elements Required for HPRT1 Expression via Thousands of Large, Programmed Genomic Deletions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajhg.2017.06.010&#34;&gt;AJHG 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HPRT1 is a &lt;strong&gt;housekeeping gene&lt;/strong&gt; (so expressed in every cell) but its regulation is not well understood.
Disruptive variants leads to the &lt;strong&gt;X-linked Lesch-Nyhan syndrome&lt;/strong&gt;.
A small proportion of affected individuals have apparently no coding variants.
Could it be because of non-coding variants?
&lt;strong&gt;This study investigates which region around this gene causes down-regulation when deleted.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick pairs of available cut sites around HPRT1 creating overlapping tiles (4,342 pairs, 27x median coverage).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce these cuts to create deletions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequence before selection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow the cells selecting for cells that don’t express the gene.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequence again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute enrichment scores for each pair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summarize that at the nucleotide level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify region with high enrichment scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;“negative” results&lt;/strong&gt; showed that only deletions of coding regions and the very near promoter are selected for by the experiment.
That means that other deletions don’t have a effect strong enough to be selected for or at least much lower than a coding deletion.
Distal non-coding variants causing subtle expression changes might still contribute to the disease but no low-hanging fruit.
At least not in this cell line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Minimizers, CNV burden, and ref-guided scaffolding</title>
          <link>/2019/02/12/minimizers-cnv-burden-and-ref-guided-scaffolding/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2019/02/12/minimizers-cnv-burden-and-ref-guided-scaffolding/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;I accumulated a huge number of articles in Feedly and I don’t know what to do about them.
One thing I decided to try was to go over them quickly and write down what I want to remember.
I don’t think I will read these kind of posts again but maybe it will help me remember or eventually find the reference again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;minimizer-indexes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minimizer indexes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to understand better minimizer indexes as they seem to be more and more important in the field.
A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/546309v1?rss=1&#34;&gt;recent preprint&lt;/a&gt; introduces the three ways to index kmers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;index fixed-size words in sets (e.g. Bloom filters)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;full-text index (e.g. FM-indexes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generic associative indexes (~hash tables).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Bloom filters we can test if a kmers is probably in a set or if it is not.
So there can be false-positives but no false-negatives.
It requires much less memory than a more naive indexation.
A Bloom filter is basically a bit array and some hash functions that map to the bit array.
To add an element it is passed to each hash function and the resulting bits turned on.
To test if an element is in the Bloom filter we can just use the hash functions again and test if all the bits are on.
When this occurs by chance, it’s a false-positive.
Elements cannot be removed from a Bloom filter.
Query time is constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FM-indexes uses Burrows-Wheeler transform to compress a text while still allowing fast substring search.
The name comes from &lt;em&gt;Full-text index in Minute space&lt;/em&gt;.
Query time as well as space is sublinear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach is described in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://genomeinformatics.github.io/mashmap/&#34;&gt;post from Adam Phillipy&lt;/a&gt;.
He describes an approach for &lt;em&gt;approximate&lt;/em&gt; mapping which might be better suited than traditional approaches when mapping long reads with higher error rates.
The basic idea is to extract a kmer from a string, for example the smallest according to an defined order.
In practice a window slides over a long string/reads and saves the minimizers in each window.
The minimizers are used to quickly find hits in the genome.
They can also be used to estimate the identity of the read alignment, avoiding a costly realignment step.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lh3/minimap2&#34;&gt;Minimap2&lt;/a&gt;, developed by Heng Li, is also using minimizer indexes to find seeds for its seed-chain-align strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;phenome-wide-burden-of-copy-number-variation-in-uk-biobank&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Phenome-wide burden of copy number variation in UK Biobank&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/545996v1?rss=1&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CNVs genotyped from arrays across almost 500M individuals using PennCNV.
The average size of the ~300K CNVs was 226 kbp.
Because individuals in the cohort are relatively healthy (enrolled at age 40-69), they used this data to create a CNV intolerance score similar to the CNV pLI from the ExAC project.
They describe in more details associations with coronary artery disease and body mas index, including some in intergenic regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;fast-and-accurate-reference-guided-scaffolding-of-draft-genomes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fast and accurate reference-guided scaffolding of draft genomes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/519637v1&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Schatz lab, RaGOO that uses minimap2 alignment to a reference to produce chromosome-level scaffold quickly.
It also identifies structural variants and can correct for apparent chimeric contigs.
The algorithm is basically three steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aligning with minimap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clustering contigs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ordering and orienting contigs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chimeric contigs can be inter-chromosomal or intra-chromosomal.
Large portions of an intra-chromosomal chimeric contigs will map uniquely to at least two distinct reference chromosomes.
A similar approach is used for intra-chromosomal chimeric contigs, using a user-defined maximum distance (default is 2 Mbp).
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/malonge/RaGOO&#34;&gt;RaGOO&lt;/a&gt; is written in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Cool tools, &#39;machine-learning&#39;, and a population-specific reference genome</title>
          <link>/2018/07/22/cool-tools-machine-learning-and-a-population-specific-reference-genome/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2018/07/22/cool-tools-machine-learning-and-a-population-specific-reference-genome/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;I accumulated a huge number of articles in Feedly and I don’t know what to do about them.
One thing I decided to try was to go over them quickly and write down what I want to remember.
I don’t think I will read these kind of posts again but maybe it will help me remember or eventually find the reference again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;genomeview - an extensible python-based genomics visualization engine&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/06/26/355636&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomeview.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34;&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;code&gt;genomeview&lt;/code&gt; implements a genomic visualization for python.
It can creates SVG file representing genomics annotation (transcripts/tracks) and reads (short/long) of a region.
This package nicely complement the bioinformatics python environment.
I like that it integrates with jupyter notebooks or could be used for interactive applications.
Among my projects, this could be integrated to my local SV assembler by showing the alignment of reads on the newly assembled sequence versus the reference sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EnsembleCNV: An ensemble machine learning algorithm to identify and genotype copy number variation using SNP array data&lt;/strong&gt;.
In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/06/27/356667&#34;&gt;their preprint&lt;/a&gt; the ensemble results from three methods are described: PennCNV, QuantiSNP and iPattern.
Part of the ensemble feature, CNV regions are derived from the calls from different methods and samples (using a network analysis and cliques finding), and then (re-)genotyped.
The machine learning part seems to be during the genotyping where a &lt;em&gt;local likelihood model is trained on both LRR and BAF&lt;/em&gt;.
Hum reading the methods quickly it seems like the &lt;em&gt;“machine learning”&lt;/em&gt; is just Gaussian mixture modeling and this types of things…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RBV: Read balance validator, a tool for prioritising copy number variations in germline conditions&lt;/strong&gt;.
Because BAF information is &lt;em&gt;underutilised&lt;/em&gt;, RBV package (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/whitneywhitford/RBV&#34;&gt;python&lt;/a&gt;) model BAF to validate or prioritize CNVs.
Here “prioritize” is in term of quality, not functional impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Qatar genome: a population-specific tool for precision medicine in the Middle East&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4927697/&#34;&gt;Hum Genome Var 2016&lt;/a&gt;).
1,161 Qataris were sequenced (~100 WGS and ~1,300 WES) and used to create a population-specific rederence that improved coverage and reduced the number of variants called.
The benefit of this reference varied in across ancestries.
One benefit of modifying the reference is that less variants needs to be interpreted and that those that are considered are likely rare variants.
Interesting: to liftover their genome they used ProgressiveCactus alignment and HalTools.
It’s a bit strange how they computed the benefit of their reference in term of coverage, showing the sum of the bases mapped (overall or at modified bases).
Of note these numbers are shown in bar plots that don’t start at 0.
They observed a 23% depth improvement at variant sites when mapping to their new reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GenomicScores: seamless access to genomewide position-specific scores from R and Bioconductor&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/advance-article/doi/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty311/4987140&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/GenomicScores&#34;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt;).
This R package simplify the utilization of position scores such as conservation.
Essentially two functions &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;gscore&lt;/code&gt; can efficiently retrieve a summary statistic (e.g. mean) of scores in a genomic region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BioVR: a platform for virtual reality assisted biological data integration and visualization&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/04/25/307769&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;).
A virtual reality tool to manipulate DNA/RNA/protein structure using an Oculus Rift and hand detection.
More of a proof-of-concept than a completely usable/useful tool but cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41576-018-0018-x&#34;&gt;The personal and clinical utility of polygenic risk scores&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. A Nature Reviews Genetics lead by Eric Topol that looks interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>SV-eQTLs in GTEx data from WGS</title>
          <link>/2018/03/31/chiang-sveqtl-2017/</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2018/03/31/chiang-sveqtl-2017/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;This is a review of “&lt;em&gt;The impact of structural variation on human gene expression&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC5406250&#34;&gt;Chiang Nat Gen 2017&lt;/a&gt;) from the Hall lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;summary&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;deep WGS&lt;/strong&gt; from 147 individuals in &lt;strong&gt;GTEx&lt;/strong&gt; they called &lt;strong&gt;SVs and eQTLs&lt;/strong&gt; across 13 tissues (RNA-seq).
For the first time they could investigate the contribution of small SVs in gene expression changes, comparing it with SNVs and indels.
They estimated that &lt;strong&gt;3.5-6.8% of eQTLs are caused by SVs&lt;/strong&gt; and that SVs tend to have a larger effect size.
Most causal SVs were &lt;strong&gt;non-coding&lt;/strong&gt; and were &lt;strong&gt;enriched&lt;/strong&gt; in or close to &lt;strong&gt;regulatory regions&lt;/strong&gt;.
They also detected an enrichment of rare SVs close to genes with outlier expressions, suggesting that rare SVs could have a high-impact on gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;methods&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WGS ~50x
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SpeedSeq pipeline: BWA-MEM + LUMPY.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SVtyper to genotype the population.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genome STRiP to detect additional CNVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QC included: homogeneous number across samples, similar frequency distribution, array-based intensity rank-sum (IRS) statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RNA-seq from GTEx across 13 tissues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eQTL detection with FastQTL
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV-only for SVs with MAF&amp;gt;.05 and 1 Mbp cis window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SNV/indels/SV joint-calling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Causal variant in eGene
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highest P-value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CAVIAR (signal magnitude and direction + LD structure).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heritability of the top SV vs 1000 top SNVs using a linear mixed model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Causal non-coding SV characterization.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grouping the SV-eQTLs by “causality score” (CAVIAR + heritability).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overlap with regulatory region: TSS, enhancers, gene 3’ end, TAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes adds 10 Kbp flanks to annotation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GWAS comparison
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subset of high-confidence GWAS SNVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overlap with lead eQTL from joint analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subset where SV was the lead eQTL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rare SVs effect
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify gene expression outliers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify rare SVs (at most two individuals).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test enrichment in gene body + 5 Kbp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV catalog: deletions (50.7%), duplications (15.0%), multiallelic CNVs (mCNVs; 6.5%), reference mobile-element insertions (rMEIs; 8.7%), inversions (0.2%) and breakends (BND; 18.9%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11% of SV-eQTLs were exonic&lt;/strong&gt; in the SV-only analysis, the majority of which followed the expected gene change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The joint eQTL calling identified 23.5K eQTLs: 85.55 SNVs, 10.9% indels, &lt;em&gt;3.5% SVs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.5%&lt;/strong&gt; of eQTLs were the identified as &lt;strong&gt;causal by CAVIAR&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;6.8%&lt;/strong&gt; of eQTLs, the &lt;strong&gt;heritability&lt;/strong&gt; of gene expression due to the top SV was higher that the one due to the additive effect of the 1K top SNVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The median effect size on gene expression was 1.3 times larger for SVs than SNVs and indels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most &lt;strong&gt;causal SV-eQTLs were enriched in&lt;/strong&gt; mCNVs and duplications, exons (from the eGene), enhancers, TFBS, 10 Kbp upstream or downstream of the eGenes (TSS or 3’ end).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only 58.2%&lt;/strong&gt; of common autosomal &lt;strong&gt;SVs were in strong LD&lt;/strong&gt; (r-squared&amp;gt;0.8) with a SNV or indel in the WGS data.
To further stress the value of WGS and SVs, they estimated that only 3.8% of common CNVs were detectable on the Omni 2.5 SNP-array platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While rare variants were in general 1.2-fold &lt;strong&gt;enriched in gene body (+-5 Kbp)&lt;/strong&gt;, the enrichment was much stronger for &lt;strong&gt;rare SVs&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;16.1-fold&lt;/strong&gt;).
Rare SVs close to expression outliers were significantly larger and duplications more frequent.
Around 80% of these SVs were CNVs altering gene dosage; ~11% were non-coding CNVs; A few were complex SVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;for-future-inspiration&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;For future inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this &lt;strong&gt;IRS&lt;/strong&gt; (intensity rank-sum) statistics that they use as validation? Is it just how concordant the calls are with array signal. If so, isn’t it validating only large CNVs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does BEDtools shuffle regions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;clever-analysis&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clever analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing the direction of the gene expression changes per SV class (exonic or not) to suggest that they are indeed causal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;questions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not sure I understand Fig 3a completely. If the x-axis represent classes of SVs based on the quantile of the causality score, shouldn’t all the decile classes have the same number of SVs (y-axis)? And shouldn’t they be one fifth of the first bar that represent the 0-0.5 quantile?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They show that the MAF is similar in SNVs, indels and SVs. Shouldn’t it be driven by the variant size? Wouldn’t we expect large deletions to be less frequent than SNVs in general?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The SVs paper from the 1000GP (Sudmant et al 2015) had tested SNV-SV eQTLs in lymphoblastoid cell lines and found 54 eQTLs (0.56%) with a lead SV-eQTL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cbrc.kaust.edu.sa/dendb/&#34;&gt;Dragon ENhancers database (DENdb)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://archive.gersteinlab.org/funseq2.1.0_data/&#34;&gt;FunSeq&lt;/a&gt; from the Gerstein lab (see Fu et al. FunSeq2 Genome Biol 2014).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Summary of our LOY paper</title>
          <link>/2017/10/23/summary-of-our-loy-paper/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/10/23/summary-of-our-loy-paper/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;intro&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;renal-cell-carcinoma&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Renal Cell Carcinoma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/html/kidrp.html&#34;&gt;Kidney Cancer: new cases and deaths&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8th most common cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;64K new cases of kidney cancer each year in US; &lt;strong&gt;15.6 per 100K&lt;/strong&gt;; 3.8% of all new cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14.4K deaths; 3.9 per 100K; &lt;strong&gt;2.4% of all cancer deaths&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;74.1%&lt;/strong&gt; surviving 5 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.6% lifetime risk to be diagnosed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Median age at diagnosis: 64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incidence is increasing but death rate and survival are improving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kidney cancer incidence rates are &lt;strong&gt;highest in Europe, North America, and Australia&lt;/strong&gt; and lowest in India, Japan, Africa, and China. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3930658/&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cigarette &lt;strong&gt;smoking&lt;/strong&gt; is a risk factor and associated with cancer stage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased &lt;strong&gt;BMI&lt;/strong&gt; is an independent risk factor for RCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hypertension&lt;/strong&gt; doubles the risk of RCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RCC represents 85-95% of all adult kidney cancer. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clevelandclinicmeded.com/medicalpubs/diseasemanagement/nephrology/renal-cell-carcinoma/&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;clear-cell-rcc&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Clear cell RCC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;60–80% of RCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;loss of chromosome 3p&lt;/strong&gt; in about 90% of the sporadic cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VHL&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;PBRM1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;SETD2&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;BAP1&lt;/em&gt;, mutated in 80%, 40%, 19% and 12% of cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inactivation of VHL leads to constitutive stabilization of the hypoxia inducible transcription factors (HIF), and abnormal activation of their downstream genes, which contribute to cancer development. The remaining three genes encode proteins involved in chromatin remodeling and histone modifications, highlighting the important role of epigenome aberration in the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;kdm5d-kdm6c&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;KDM5D &amp;amp; KDM6C&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why them ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their X-linked homologs involved in ccRCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epigenetic factors and 3 out the 4 most hypermutated genes are too (PBRM1, SETD2 and BAP1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deletion of KDM5D has been detected in 52% of prostate cancers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KDM5D&lt;/strong&gt; encodes a lysine-specific &lt;strong&gt;histone H3 demethylase&lt;/strong&gt;, which plays an important role in epigenetic regulation.
Its down-regulation could have a functional impact because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knockdown of KDM5D through RNA-interference (RNAi) increases cell proliferation and reduces apoptosis in prostate cancer, suggesting a tumor suppressor function for this gene.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;85% similar and same functions as KDM5C (chr X), which is recurrently mutated in ccRCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KDM5C is recurrently mutated in ccRCC and its inactivation leads to genomic instability in ccRCC through deregulation of H3K4 methylation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KDM6C demethylates H3K27&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;83% similar and similar function as KDM6A (chr X), which is recurrently mutated in ccRCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KDM6A is recurrently mutated in ccRCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested whether &lt;strong&gt;KDM5D expression has an anti-tumor activity&lt;/strong&gt; in renal cancer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compared RCC cell lines from male patients and selected the one with no KDM5D expression (likely LOY).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ectopic expression of KDM5D reduced cell viability to 65%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other candidates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TMSB4Y has recently been identified as a tumor suppressor gene downregulated in male breast cancers16, but not connected to ccRCC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Cancer numbers</title>
          <link>/2017/10/21/cancer-numbers/</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/10/21/cancer-numbers/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These numbers are based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.3322/caac.21387/full&#34;&gt;Cancer Statistics 2017&lt;/a&gt;, partly projections for 2017 in the US.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./CancerStats2017.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;incidence&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Incidence&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cancers with the highest incidence are &lt;strong&gt;prostate&lt;/strong&gt; cancer in man (20%) and &lt;strong&gt;breast&lt;/strong&gt; cancer in woman (30%).
The second and third are &lt;strong&gt;lung&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;colon&lt;/strong&gt; cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;death&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Death&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lung&lt;/strong&gt; cancer is by far the &lt;strong&gt;most deadly cancer&lt;/strong&gt;, responsible for &lt;em&gt;25-27%&lt;/em&gt; of cancer deaths.
It is followed by &lt;strong&gt;colon&lt;/strong&gt; cancer and &lt;strong&gt;prostate/breast&lt;/strong&gt; in male/female.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brain&lt;/strong&gt; cancer is the most deadly cancer in the young population (&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt;40 years old&lt;/strong&gt;).
It is the second most common cancer after leukemia in this age group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;gender-ratio&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Gender ratio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lifetime probability to be diagnosed with invasive cancer is &lt;strong&gt;40.8% for men&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;37.5% for women&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidence of &lt;em&gt;liver&lt;/em&gt; cancer is three times higher in men than in women.
Even more for &lt;em&gt;esophagus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;larynx&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;bladder&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidence are higher in women for cancers of the &lt;em&gt;thyroid&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;anus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;gallbladder&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some disparities in mortality is driven by earlier diagnosis in women.
Same for incidence because of the different environmental exposure (e.g. smoking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-numbers&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Other numbers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Height is positively associated with cancer incidence and death!?
Apparently because taller individuals have more cells, and having more cells means more chance of getting cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Lit Digest - Testing overlap between genomic regions</title>
          <link>/2017/10/19/lit-digest-testing-overlap-between-genomic-regions/</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/10/19/lit-digest-testing-overlap-between-genomic-regions/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;lola-enrichment-analysis-for-genomic-region-sets-and-regulatory-elements-in-r-and-bioconductor&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;LOLA: enrichment analysis for genomic region sets and regulatory elements in R and Bioconductor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv612&#34;&gt;Sheffield 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding on the gene-centric enrichment analyses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/LOLA/&#34;&gt;R package&lt;/a&gt; efficiently tests for significant overlap (Fisher test) and report results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user specify the &lt;em&gt;universe&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. all the regions that could have been selected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To test enrichment in differential-like analysis where a subset of regions is tested for overlap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not directly feasible for CNVs expect if we provide a set of control regions as &lt;em&gt;universe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;exploring-massive-genome-scale-datasets-with-the-genometricorr-package.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring massive, genome scale datasets with the GenometriCorr package.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22693437&#34;&gt;Favorov 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R package that efficiently calculates the spatial correlation between two sets of genomic intervals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;genome-wide-study-of-correlations-between-genomic-features-and-their-relationship-with-the-regulation-of-gene-expression.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Genome-wide study of correlations between genomic features and their relationship with the regulation of gene expression.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25627242&#34;&gt;Kravatsky 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed the criteria for the assessment of genome track inhomogeneity and correlations between two genome tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Epilepsy genes candidates</title>
          <link>/2017/10/02/epilepsy-genes-candidates/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/10/02/epilepsy-genes-candidates/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;We had a few candidate genes that could be affected by non-coding CNVs.
We could try to recreate the deletions using CRISPR but we need to know the cell type to phenotype (and how/what to phenotype).
I’ll try to find information from the various databases and from publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our collaborators can differentiate cells into &lt;strong&gt;glutamatergic&lt;/strong&gt; neurons (as opposed to &lt;em&gt;GABA-ergic&lt;/em&gt;).
For the phenotype, we could monitor the gene expression levels.
It’s an intermediate phenotype but could be convincing enough.
Otherwise, Knut mentioned &lt;em&gt;“neural network effects such as Ca++ flux”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;candidate-genes&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Candidate genes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SZT2, DNM1, MRS2, KCTD7, ST3GAL3, CELSR1, CACNA1A for the CNVs in unique regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SERPINI1, SCN2A, SCN1A, CPA6, BRAF, WWOX, MMP27, N6AMT1, MYO3A, HCN1, SCN5A, CLN6, EPM2A, FAM63B for the CNV in unique regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;glutamatergic&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Glutamatergic?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply means “related to glutamate”.
Ok, that was easy, next…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glutamate?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Glutamate&lt;/strong&gt; or glutamic acid is an amino acid.
In our case I think we are more interested in its role as a neurotransmitter.
The &lt;strong&gt;most abundant neurotransmitter&lt;/strong&gt; (90% of human brain connections).
Glutamate binds and activates receptors (AMPA, kainate, NMDA) that in turn open membrane channels that let ions pass through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;some diseases an excess of glutamate&lt;/strong&gt; can lead to cell death when its transporters are not effectively removing it from the extracellular space.
This type of glutamate excess has been observed in strokes, autism, ID, AD and &lt;strong&gt;epilepsy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In epilepsy, an epileptic phenotype could be recreated though micro-injection of glutamate.
It caused a &lt;strong&gt;depolarization&lt;/strong&gt; that can become stronger with some kind of feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;kctd7&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;KCTD7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two brothers with a severe form of &lt;strong&gt;epilepsy&lt;/strong&gt; showed the &lt;strong&gt;excess of glutamine&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27742667&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;).
From exome sequencing they found a frame-shift mutation in KCTD7 and performed some experiments in animal models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] KCTD7 has an impact on K+ fluxes, neurotransmitter synthesis and neuronal function, and that malfunction of the encoded protein may lead to progressive myoclonus epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-coding CNV we found was located downstream of the gene in an active and conserved region.
It overlaps an eQTL associated with the gene’s expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;szt2&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SZT2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also called “Transcript increased in &lt;strong&gt;glutamate&lt;/strong&gt; resistance” because it was &lt;em&gt;“upregulated in resistance to oxidative glutamate toxicity”&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20045724&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] oxidative glutamate toxicity and excitotoxicity are plausible mechanisms underlying epileptogenesis caused by SZT2 mutations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3769928/&#34;&gt;Ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-coding CNV we found was located downstream of the gene, overlapping a DNase site associated with the gene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;hcn1&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;HCN1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HCN1 channels selectively regulate glutamatergic synaptic release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HCN channels inhibit glutamate synaptic release by suppressing the activity of low threshold voltage-gated T- (CaV3.2) type Ca2+ channels&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HCN1 channels are predominantly located at glutamatergic synaptic terminals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3068302/&#34;&gt;Ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also glutamate levels affect HCN1 trafficking (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2863223/&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-coding CNV was an intronic deletion.
Not confirmed but with a clear coverage drop.
It overlaps an eQTL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cacna1a&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CACNA1A&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much except it seems like an important epilepsy gene that may involve glutamatergic neurons and other types of mechanisms.
Pathways from ByoSystems: Glutamatergic synapse (but also GABAergic synapse).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;scn1a&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SCN1A&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dravet syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cpa6&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CPA6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knockdown lead to downregulation of glutamate transporters (&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0152905&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;epm2a&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;EPM2A&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something about EPM2A- mice and how active-caspase-3 appears only in glutamatergic neurons (&lt;a href=&#34;https://molecularbrain.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1756-6606-7-7&#34;&gt;ref.&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] homeostasis of glutamate transporter GLT-1, called EAAT2 (Excitatory AminoAcid Transporter 2) in humans, is affected in mouse primary astrocytes lacking either EPM2A or EPM2B genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5472677/&#34;&gt;Ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;n6amt1&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;N6AMT1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something about Glutamine Methyltransferase but not related to the neurotransmitter I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mrs2-st3gal3-celsr1-serpini1-scn2a-braf-wwox-mmp27-myo3a-scn5a-cln6-fam63b&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MRS2, ST3GAL3, CELSR1, SERPINI1, SCN2A, BRAF, WWOX, MMP27, MYO3A, SCN5A, CLN6, FAM63B&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;dnm1&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DNM1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosgenetics/article?id=10.1371/journal.pgen.1005347&#34;&gt;Asinof et al.&lt;/a&gt; says the epilepsy phenotype comes from GABA neurons and other phenotypes (ID) from glutamatergic neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Genome graphs</title>
          <link>/2017/09/23/genome-graphs/</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/09/23/genome-graphs/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;why-genome-graphs&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why genome graphs ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better genome reference.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher mapping rate in the presence of variation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less “biased” toward the fixed linear European reference genome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to update. No more major version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better annotation for non-SNV variants.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More general and intuitive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only one way to place indels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex variants involving several canonical types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved variant calling.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrating known variants. Would be useful for SVs with breakpoint resolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In highly polymorphic regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;challenges&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map efficiently reads to graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predict the sequence of the allele(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detect new variation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project annotation to graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;drawbacks&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Difficult to integrate CNVs or SVs with imprecise breakpoints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-ideas&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other ideas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use haplotype information for better mapping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phasing from graph-wide estimation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To represent/use a de novo assembly without the need linearize it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To analyze different types of variants together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;types-of-graphs&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Types of graphs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A-Bruijn graphs. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC525693/&#34;&gt;Used for MSA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cactus graph: every edge is in at most one cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;tools&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vgteam/vg&#34;&gt;vg toolbox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vgteam&#34;&gt;Other tools from the vg team&lt;/a&gt;. E.g. sequenceTubeMap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/hisat2/index.shtml&#34;&gt;HISAT2&lt;/a&gt;, graph-based alignment of next generation sequencing reads to a population of genomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;talks&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/GenomeRef/variation-reference-graphs-and-the-variation-graph-toolkit-vg&#34;&gt;Variation reference graphs and the variation graph toolkit vg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1bbl2zY4qWQ0yYBHhoVuXb79HdgajRotIUa_VEn3kTpI/edit#slide=id.p&#34;&gt;Slides: Resequencing against a human whole genome variation graph (vg)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdaFFOD50og&#34;&gt;Video: The Human Genome Variation Map Graph Bake-Off&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;tweets&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tweets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PlantEvolution/status/932983550818816000&#34;&gt;A workflow for 1001 genomes project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;papers&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cactus-algorithms-for-genome-multiple-sequence-alignment&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cactus: Algorithms for genome multiple sequence alignment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3166836/&#34;&gt;Paten, Genome Research 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;strong&gt;Cactus alignment program&lt;/strong&gt; is introduced.
It allows for &lt;strong&gt;alignment of multiple genomes using a Cactus graph representation&lt;/strong&gt;.
Cactus graphs are particularly good at representing/embedding large rearrangements and copy number variation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Needs more reading.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;improved-genome-inference-in-the-mhc-using-a-population-reference-graph&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Improved genome inference in the MHC using a population reference graph&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articles/PMC4449272&#34;&gt;Dilthey, Nature Genetics 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They introduced the concept of a &lt;strong&gt;population reference graph&lt;/strong&gt; integrating known variants and multiple “alternate” reference sequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used this approach on the MHC region of chromosome 6.
This is the famously polymorphic HLA region.
They build the graph with 8 alternate reference haplotypes, known HLA alleles, and ~90K SNPs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this proof of concept, they show that the genome inference is improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their workflow to build the graph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple sequence alignment of reference sequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collapse MSA into graph if sequence identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add SNPs where possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then to infer the allele of each sample:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HMM from kmer counts to infer the best path in graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a chromotype from the best paths.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use variant caller on chromotype to find new variants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add new variants to chromotype.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their comparison they found a gain in regions with paralogous.
The inclusion of variants called from the chromotype didn’t improve the performance much, most likely because this regions has been extensively studied and genotyped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graph approach makes use of a greater proportion of the reads, hence analyzing more of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also compared the chromotypes derived from different approach do Moleculo long reads.
They showed that the graph-based chromotypes are more similar, although Platypus looks very good also.
It had more perfectly aligned reads, but also more of the very badly aligned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although only 1% of the genome could gain from such approach, they mention other regions of high diversity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KIR region&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Olfactory gene clusters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inversion on 17q21.31&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limitations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kmer approach not suited for low-complexity regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HMM doesn’t integrate long range haplotype information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;canonical-stable-general-mapping-using-context-schemes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Canonical, stable, general mapping using context schemes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articles/PMC4757953/&#34;&gt;Novak, Bioinformatics 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;building-a-pan-genome-reference-for-a-population&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Building a pan-genome reference for a population&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4424974/&#34;&gt;Nguyen, J Comput Biol 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extension of the Cactus program to a set of closely related genomes.
The goal is to align genomes together and find the best ordering of the homology blocks that best represent the underlying genome.
The results is a representation of the pan-genome of the population, particularly useful for visualization, variant description and potentially read mapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;genome-graphs&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Genome Graphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/101378&#34;&gt;Novak, bioRxiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several genome graphs structures are compared and shown to be superior to linear representations when mapping reads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They tested 5 regions of the human genome: the major histocompatibility complex (MHC), the killer cell immunoglobulin-like receptors (LRC_KIR) region, the spinal muscular atrophy (SMA) locus, and the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genome graphs improves the amount of read mapped but especially the amount of perfect mapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;coordinates-and-intervals-in-graph-based-reference-genomes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coordinates and intervals in graph-based reference genomes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articles/PMC5437615&#34;&gt;Rand, BMC bioinformatics 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different strategies to define coordinates and intervals in a graph are presented.
The goal is to find a good way to annotate genome graphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For coordinates we would want:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;spatiality&lt;/em&gt;: nearby bases have similar coordinates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;readability&lt;/em&gt;: concise and interpretable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;monotonicity&lt;/em&gt;: increment along the genome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;backward compatibility&lt;/em&gt;: supports updates somewhere else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They propose two offset-based coordinate systems.
One way is to hierarchically partition the graph by choosing main regions and alternate loci as baseline for the offsets.
This is backward compatible but there is no spatiality.
The other way, sequential partitioning, is to divide the main path every time there is a fork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For naming regions we would want:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;vertical spatiality&lt;/em&gt;: are two regions variants of each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;horizontal spatiality&lt;/em&gt;: are two regions close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;monotonicity&lt;/em&gt;: which region comes first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally they propose two ways to represent intervals in the graph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;single-path&lt;/em&gt; intervals contains the start, end and information about the path in the graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;multipath&lt;/em&gt; intervals uses either a &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;/em&gt; subpaths (where the path must go through) or a &lt;em&gt;fuzzy&lt;/em&gt; path (central path and threshold).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-graph-extension-of-the-positional-burrows-wheeler-transform-and-its-applications&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A graph extension of the positional Burrows-Wheeler transform and its applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5505026/&#34;&gt;Novak, Algorithms Mol Biol 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generalization of the PBWT (positional BWT) to genome graph is introduced, called gPBWT.
It’s a compressible representation of haplotypes in a graph that can be efficiently queried.
They conclude that the haplotype information could be incorporated into graph-based read mappers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;modelling-haplotypes-with-respect-to-reference-cohort-variation-graphs&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Modelling haplotypes with respect to reference cohort variation graphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28881971&#34;&gt;Rosen, Bioinformatics 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing on the haplotype representation from Novak 2017, they model recombination and haplotypes variation in the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;genome-graphs-and-the-evolution-of-genome-inference&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Genome graphs and the evolution of genome inference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articles/PMC5411762&#34;&gt;Paten, Genome Research 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;comparative-annotation-toolkit-cat---simultaneous-clade-and-personal-genome-annotation&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comparative Annotation Toolkit (CAT) - simultaneous clade and personal genome annotation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/12/08/231118.full.pdf+html&#34;&gt;Fiddes, bioRxiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A toolkit to compare assemblies and genomes.
It uses Cactus graphs and Augustus under the hood to respectively align and annotate the assemblies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sequence-variation-aware-genome-references-and-read-mapping-with-the-variation-graph-toolkit&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sequence variation aware genome references and read mapping with the variation graph toolkit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/12/15/234856&#34;&gt;Garrison, bioRxiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paper presenting the &lt;strong&gt;vg&lt;/strong&gt; toolkit that provides ways to &lt;strong&gt;create/edit variation graphs&lt;/strong&gt; and perform &lt;strong&gt;read mapping&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;variant calling&lt;/strong&gt; on it.
&lt;strong&gt;vg scales to&lt;/strong&gt; large genome like &lt;strong&gt;the human genome&lt;/strong&gt;.
Contrary to existing approaches, vg doesn’t use or need an initial linear reference to build and use the graph.
A vg graph can be created from a linear reference + VCF, or from a set of sequences to align to each other.
New variant can be added easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variation graph is a set of nodes, edges and paths.
Nodes can be traversed in two direction, the second representing the reverse complement of the first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For alignment, vg uses a classic &lt;strong&gt;seed-extend&lt;/strong&gt; through indexes.
The main difference is that it uses &lt;strong&gt;two representations&lt;/strong&gt; for the two steps.
The super-maximal exact match (&lt;strong&gt;SMEM&lt;/strong&gt;) seed identification is performed from the &lt;strong&gt;indexed&lt;/strong&gt; xg graph using the GCSA2 library.
For paired reads, the seeds for both reads are searched at the same time and SMEMs that match the distance are preferred.
The best SMEMs are chosen using the ML though a Markov model.
Secondary seeds are retrieved by iteratively masking the best paths.
For each seed the subgraph is retrieved and converted into a directed acyclic graph (&lt;strong&gt;DAG&lt;/strong&gt;) to perform the full read alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;vg was &lt;strong&gt;compared to bwa mem&lt;/strong&gt; on simulated and real read from a Ashkenazi Jewish male genome.
In regions with &lt;strong&gt;no variants&lt;/strong&gt;, vg performed slightly &lt;strong&gt;worse&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; gave a &lt;strong&gt;better&lt;/strong&gt; performance in &lt;strong&gt;regions with variants&lt;/strong&gt;.
This superiority was stronger for single ends as the paired end information helped figure out the correct mapping in many cases.
On real reads, vg mapped a similar number of reads but with better quality, especially more perfect matches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More impressively, the &lt;strong&gt;coverage at known indel location&lt;/strong&gt; (from GIAB annotation) was &lt;strong&gt;much more balanced&lt;/strong&gt; with vg and independent of the variant size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other application uses graphs built from genome alignments of different yeast strains.
Again they show that reads map better in the vg graph than the reference from another strain.
Even removing the relevant strain from the graph showed good mapping performance.
I’m just a bit surprised that aligning to the relevant strain only is much better than the graph with several strains (including the relevant strain).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the future developments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving &lt;strong&gt;mapping&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;variant calling&lt;/strong&gt; algorithms, e.g. using long range &lt;strong&gt;haplotype&lt;/strong&gt; information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allele-specific&lt;/strong&gt; expression, benefiting from unbiased mapping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Splice-aware&lt;/strong&gt; RNAseq mapping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration of &lt;strong&gt;structural variants&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vg uses a bidirected DNA sequence graph structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Variant callers that use information of known variant: FreeBayes and GATK HaplotypeCaller (1000GP).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vg is multithreaded C++11. It uses protobuf to represent graphs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They introduce a protobuf alignment format: &lt;strong&gt;GAM&lt;/strong&gt; for Graph Alignment Map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;xg&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;strong&gt;succinct representation of a vg graph&lt;/strong&gt;, more memory and time efficient, used for read mapping and other operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the &lt;strong&gt;distance&lt;/strong&gt; measure defined ? It’s used during read mapping. They mention the use of nearby paths.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some reads were mapped at different locations using linear vs graph approaches. Many of them because of repeats such as satellite DNA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GraphTyper is mentioned in the discussion. It’s quite different as it only realigns locally reads into a graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;snv-caller-that-uses-known-variantshaplotypes&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SNV caller that uses known variants/haplotypes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;freebayes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;FreeBayes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By Erik Garrison.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ekg/freebayes&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1207.3907&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bayesian statistical framework which is capable of modeling multiallelic loci in sets of individuals with non-uniform copy number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FreeBayes is haplotype-based, in the sense that it calls variants based on the literal sequences of reads aligned to a particular target, not their precise alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should be used in a population of samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finds the most-likely combination of genotype in the population.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Haplotype is short-range haplotype (max 10s of bp).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;gatk-haplotype-caller&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GATK Haplotype Caller&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://software.broadinstitute.org/gatk/best-practices/workflow?id=11145&#34;&gt;GATK documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HaplotypeCaller is capable of calling SNPs and indels simultaneously via local de-novo assembly of haplotypes in an active region. In other words, whenever the program encounters a region showing signs of variation, it discards the existing mapping information and completely reassembles the reads in that region. This allows the HaplotypeCaller to be more accurate when calling regions that are traditionally difficult to call, for example when they contain different types of variants close to each other. It also makes the HaplotypeCaller much better at calling indels than position-based callers like UnifiedGenotyper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gatkforums.broadinstitute.org/gatk/discussion/4148/hc-overview-how-the-haplotypecaller-works&#34;&gt;How it works&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define active regions, i.e. with sign of variation. Using a per-bp activity score.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-assemble reads to list possible haplotypes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align reads to each haplotype to derive per-read haplotype likelihoods. Using a HMM alignment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign sample genotypes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Lit Digest - Non-coding variants in regulatory regions</title>
          <link>/2017/09/22/lit-digest-non-coding-variants-in-regulatory-regions/</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/09/22/lit-digest-non-coding-variants-in-regulatory-regions/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;genome-wide-analysis-of-noncoding-regulatory-mutations-in-cancer&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Genome-wide analysis of noncoding regulatory mutations in cancer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25261935&#34;&gt;Weinhold &amp;amp; Jacobsen et al., Nature Genetics 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;863 tumors from TCGA and co.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify &lt;strong&gt;recurrent non-coding variants in cancer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PLEKHS1, WDR74, SDHD had such variants in upstream regulatory elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promoter/enhancer have &lt;em&gt;similar rate of somatic mutation&lt;/em&gt; as transcribed regions (~3 per Mb), and lower than intergenic (~6 per Mb), supporting the presence of functional variants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used three approaches to identify functional ncSNV candidates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;hotspot&lt;/strong&gt; analysis, aiming at cluster of variants within 50 bp of each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;regional recurrence&lt;/strong&gt; analysis, grouping the variants by regions and detecting recurrence compared to neighboring regions or the entire genome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;TFBS&lt;/strong&gt; analysis, to find mutations that create/disrupts ETS binding sites. Apparently ETS plays a role in cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the top hits were located in regulatory regions of known cancer genes (pv=3.4e-4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most significant hotspot is in &lt;strong&gt;TERT promoter&lt;/strong&gt; and consists of two recurrent mutations across 38 and 15 tumors, and &lt;strong&gt;7 cancer types&lt;/strong&gt;.
TERT tended to be &lt;strong&gt;more expressed&lt;/strong&gt; in mutated samples.
Fun fact: the C-&amp;gt;T transitions create novel ETS binding sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second most significant hotspot in in &lt;strong&gt;PLEKHS1 promoter&lt;/strong&gt;.
Again two sites, with 11 and 12 mutations over 20 samples and &lt;strong&gt;5 cancer types&lt;/strong&gt;.
The gene’s &lt;strong&gt;expression was lower&lt;/strong&gt; in mutated samples.
In bladder cancer, 40% of the samples carried one of these two mutations.
Fun fact: also a C-&amp;gt;T transition; each site is flanked by 10 bp palindromes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regional recurrence identified enrichment in larger regions, grouping the variants by functional class (enhancer, promoter, 5’ UTR, 3’UTR).
They tested both &lt;strong&gt;local enrichment&lt;/strong&gt;, comparing the mutation rate in neighboring regions, and &lt;strong&gt;global enrichment&lt;/strong&gt;, comparing the mutation rate in the same functional class and with similar DNA replication timing.
&lt;em&gt;I guess DNA replication timing affects the mutation rate ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TERT was again the strongest hit.
The second and third hits were the promoter and 5’ UTR of &lt;strong&gt;WDR74&lt;/strong&gt;.
This gene had no coding mutation but 35 non-coding variants in a ~1 Kb region at the promoter region.
No gene expression changes this time.
Overall, 5% of the tumors had a mutation in this region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TFBS approach intended to find mutation similar to the TERT examples, that either create or disrupt ETS binding sites.
From a short list of candidates, they focused on &lt;strong&gt;SDHD&lt;/strong&gt; which was also high in the regional recurrence list.
In this case, C-&amp;gt;T transitions disrupted a existing ETS binding sites, consistent with a &lt;strong&gt;reduced expression&lt;/strong&gt; of the gene.
The mutations occurred &lt;strong&gt;exclusively in melanoma samples&lt;/strong&gt;.
Because the variants were close enough to a coding region, they could use exome sequencing data to investigate more samples and even identified a third putative ETS site.
They showed that around 10% of melanoma samples have such a mutation and provided further support that these sites regulate the gene’s expression.
Samples with SDHD mutation had a significantly shorter overall survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interesting study&lt;/strong&gt;.
I like how they used the strong/known association in TERT to generalize and identify other with weaker effect.
It also showed the usefulness of performing &lt;strong&gt;different analysis&lt;/strong&gt; to better narrow down the list of leads to follow.
The way they &lt;strong&gt;used orthogonal data&lt;/strong&gt; (RNA-seq, WES or Encode) to add support to the original findings was good too.
The paper was pleasant to read as well, not too dense and not too jargon heavy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Lit Digest - SV and long-read sequencing</title>
          <link>/2017/09/20/lit-digest-sv-and-long-read-sequencing/</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/09/20/lit-digest-sv-and-long-read-sequencing/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many more SVs ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which types of SVs ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;identifying-structural-variants-using-linked-read-sequencing-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Identifying structural variants using linked-read sequencing data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/09/18/190454&#34;&gt;Elyanow, biorXiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better than other methods…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mapping-and-phasing-of-structural-variation-in-patient-genomes-using-nanopore-sequencing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mapping And Phasing Of Structural Variation In Patient Genomes Using Nanopore Sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/04/24/129379&#34;&gt;Stancu, bioRxiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 patients with congenital abnormalities, with MinION (11x/16x).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better at finding complex chromothripsis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3K novel SVs, majority being duplication &amp;lt;200 bp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phasing showed the de novo chromothripsis occurred in paternal chromosomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helps a lot for complex SVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;accurate-detection-of-complex-structural-variations-using-single-molecule-sequencing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accurate detection of complex structural variations using single molecule sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/07/28/169557&#34;&gt;Sedlazeck, bioRxiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find much more novel than TGP ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show that many translocation calls from short read caller are wrong (85%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;hysa-a-hybrid-structural-variant-assembly-approach-using-next-generation-and-single-molecule-sequencing-technologies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;HySA: a Hybrid Structural variant Assembly approach using next-generation and single-molecule sequencing technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC5411774&#34;&gt;Fan, Genome Research 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better job than Chaisson’s SMRT-SV ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;discovery-and-genotyping-of-structural-variation-from-long-read-haploid-genome-sequence-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discovery and genotyping of structural variation from long-read haploid genome sequence data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC5411763&#34;&gt;Huddleston, Genome Research 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 haploid genomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long-read is much more sensitive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highest gain for “small” SVs: 7bp - 1 Kbp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;90% SVs are novel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;60% can be genotyped with short reads once alternate allele is included.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genotyped in 30 TGP samples. Some SVs look fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Haploid is very useful for detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;resolving-the-complexity-of-the-human-genome-using-single-molecule-sequencing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resolving the complexity of the human genome using single-molecule sequencing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC4317254&#34;&gt;Chaisson, Nature 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolve inversions, complex insertions and long tandem repeats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enrichment in long short STR regions and complex insertions (?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong enrichment of STRs (15x) among closed gaps. 78% of the gaps were covered by STR more than 10%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;85% of the CNVs were novel, especially for insertions (92%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2.8x enrichment of STR insertions compared to deletions. STR insertions were 2.9x longer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STR insertions clustered at the last 5 Mbp of the chromosomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thousands of STR insertions within genes, 2 in exons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other complex insertions enriched in regions already enriched in MEI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;L1 and SVA insertions are found adjacent to repeats, more than in 1KGP or short read catalogs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;68% of inversions flanked by inverted repeats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;assembly-and-diploid-architecture-of-an-individual-human-genome-via-single-molecule-technologies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assembly and diploid architecture of an individual human genome via single-molecule technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC4646949&#34;&gt;Pendleton, Nature Methods 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identified complex SVs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phased SNVs and SVs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identified large tandem repeats and suggest that TR are larger than in the reference genome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observed DNA transduction when MEI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex STR-like insertion within STRs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4.2% of SVs are complex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inversions are enriched for complexity (55%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Misc</title>
          <link>/2017/08/20/misc/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/08/20/misc/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;misc&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Misc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cancer-chromatin-loop-and-svs&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cancer, chromatin loop and SVs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromatin loop anchor points (LAPs) as sites of regulatory importance but also genomic fragility.
They harbour an excess of SV breakpoints in cancers, are prone to double strand breaks in somatic cells, and are bound by DNA repair complex proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/07/21/166934&#34;&gt;Kaiser &amp;amp; Semple bioRxiv 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;te-suppression-in-cancer&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;TE suppression in cancer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TE suppression proposed as a mechanism for immune escape in acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) and myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS).
TE are less expressed in high-risk vs low-risk, or in resistant cancers.
Too much TE expressed would cause interferon signaling and cancer cell killing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-017-07356-9&#34;&gt;Colombo et al Sci. Reports 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;hugo-and-blogdown&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hugo and Blogdown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m hearing more and more about &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; website and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;Blogdown&lt;/a&gt; seems to be the R package to build and manage one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is Hugo better than Jekyll ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faster apparently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier workflow, less things to install.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Templates a much cooler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seamless integration of RMarkdown (through Blogdown).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogdown was written by the same person who wrote knitr (Yihui Xie).
He also wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/bookdown&#34;&gt;bookdown&lt;/a&gt; and works at RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://talesofr.wordpress.com/2017/08/18/starting-a-rmarkdown-blog-with-bookdown-hugo-github/&#34;&gt;How to set up Hugo + Blogdown on GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;dplyr-tricks&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;dplyr tricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;enquo&lt;/code&gt; to enquote a variable and &lt;code&gt;!!&lt;/code&gt; to unquote it.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enchufa2.es/archives/programming-with-dplyr-by-using-dplyr.html&#34;&gt;For example&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;starwars_mean &amp;lt;- function(var) {
  var &amp;lt;- enquo(var)
  starwars %&amp;gt;%
    group_by(!!var) %&amp;gt;%
    summarise(mean_height = mean(height, na.rm = TRUE),
            mean_mass = mean(mass, na.rm = TRUE),
            count = n())
}

starwars_mean(homeworld)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mix-multiple-graphs-with-ggplot2&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mix multiple graphs with ggplot2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the ggpubr functions, multi graphs panels can be produced, with aligned axis if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sthda.com/english/wiki/ggplot2-easy-way-to-mix-multiple-graphs-on-the-same-page&#34;&gt;Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;joy-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Joy Plots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joy plots are several density curves horizontally aligned and overlapping each other slightly.
It’s a cool way to visualize progression or gradually different profiles.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://mran.microsoft.com/web/packages/ggjoy/vignettes/gallery.html&#34;&gt;Some examples&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/clauswilke/ggjoy&#34;&gt;R package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Testing the quality of an assembly</title>
          <link>/2017/08/10/testing-the-quality-of-an-assembly/</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/08/10/testing-the-quality-of-an-assembly/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;mapping-reads&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mapping reads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;coverage-analysis&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coverage analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regions with unusual coverage might be mis-assembled (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23358380&#34; title=&#34;Sequence assembly demystified&#34;&gt;Nagarajan &amp;amp; Pop&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coverage is too high -&amp;gt; collapse of a repeat.
Coverage is too low -&amp;gt; incorrect join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;calling-snps&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Calling SNPs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An excess of SNPs might be a sign of mis-assemblies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If assembling an haploid genome, there should not be any SNPs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC4248323&#34; title=&#34;Single haplotype assembly of the human genome from a hydatidiform mole Karyn&#34;&gt;Steinberg et al&lt;/a&gt;, ~80K SNVs were found when aligning reads to their haploid assembly.
80% of those overlapped repeat regions.
34 regions (49 Mb) had a high SNV density (per Kbp, &amp;gt;2 SD deviation).
They state that because these regions are duplicated, these SNVs likely come from paralogs.
They also mapped the reads to the reference genome and found ~100K heterozygous SNVs.
This also supports the hypothesis of paralogs and repeat sequences confusing the variant calling.
So not due to mis-assembly ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;tools&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMOSvalidate statistically analyzes mate-pair orientations and separations, repeat content, depth-of-coverage, correlated polymorphisms in the read alignments, and read alignment breakpoints to identify structurally suspicious regions of the assembly. The suspicious regions identified by individual metrics are then clustered and combined to identify (with high confidence) regions that are mis-assembled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-bac-ends&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using BAC ends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I understand correctly the end sequences of a BAC clones are sequenced, maybe with Sanger sequencing (500 bp).
The BAC clone is also “fingerprinted” to estimate the insert-size.
So it’s some kind of super-mate pair information as the BAC can range from 80-350 Kbp and 500 bp flanks are sequenced.
The BAC ends are used to validate, order and join contigs (e.g. from finished BAC sequence).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discordant orientation or size of the BAC ends mapped to the assembly identify mis-assembled regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC4248323&#34; title=&#34;Single haplotype assembly of the human genome from a hydatidiform mole Karyn&#34;&gt;Steinberg et al&lt;/a&gt; used BAC ends to identify regions with potential deletions or insertions in the assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-long-reads&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using long reads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC4248323&#34; title=&#34;Single haplotype assembly of the human genome from a hydatidiform mole Karyn&#34;&gt;Steinberg et al&lt;/a&gt; used Pacbio reads to assess the quality of the assembly. Specifically they looked for regions with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;low-coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“cliffs”, i.e. abrupt drop in coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inversions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-a-reference-genome&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using a reference genome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gigascience.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/2047-217X-2-10&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; used COMPASS to compute three metrics from the alignment to a reference genome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;validity: the fraction of aligned assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multiplicity: “ratio of the length of alignable assembled sequence to covered sequence on the reference; higher multiplicity implies expansion of repeats in the assembly, lower multiplicity implies repeat collapse”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parsimony: multiplicity divided by validity, i.e. size of the assembly divided by the aligned reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.springernature.com/lw785/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1186%2F2047-217X-2-10/MediaObjects/13742_2013_Article_29_Fig7_HTML.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;others&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other approaches include comparison with transcriptome data or reference sequence of closely related organisms (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23358380&#34; title=&#34;Sequence assembly demystified&#34;&gt;Nagarajan &amp;amp; Pop 2013&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Single Cell RNA-seq and GBM</title>
          <link>/2017/05/23/single-cell-rna-seq-and-gbm/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/05/23/single-cell-rna-seq-and-gbm/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;Three studies used single cell RNA-seq on brain cancer tumors.
They also called large CNA from this data.
How ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;scrna-highlights-intra-tumoral-heterogeneity-in-primary-glioblastoma&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;scRNA highlights intra-tumoral heterogeneity in primary glioblastoma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4123637/&#34;&gt;Patel et al. (Science 2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intra-tumoral heterogeneity is thought to be an important factor of treatment resistance and relapses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GBM is one of the most lethal human malignancy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They show that known &lt;strong&gt;suptype&lt;/strong&gt; classifier for GBMs are &lt;strong&gt;actually expressed&lt;/strong&gt; differently &lt;strong&gt;across the cells&lt;/strong&gt; from the &lt;strong&gt;same tumor&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To infer large CNA they &lt;em&gt;averaged&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;em&gt;relative expression&lt;/em&gt; across large regions.
They actually average the gene expression using a &lt;em&gt;sliding window&lt;/em&gt; of 100 genes.
Hence for each of the 6,000 expressed gene they compute this average expression and use it to &lt;em&gt;cluster cells&lt;/em&gt;.
For the &lt;em&gt;heatmap&lt;/em&gt;, the signal was normalized using the control (bulk RNA-seq from normal brain samples).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They profile 430 cells from 5 glioblastomas using SMART-seq.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They excluded genes and cells with low coverage. They ended up with ~6,000 genes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They also have bulk RNA-seq from the tumor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;scrna-supports-developmental-hierarchy-in-human-oligodendroglioma&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;scRNA supports developmental hierarchy in human oligodendroglioma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v539/n7628/full/nature20123.html&#34;&gt;Tirosh et al. (Nature 2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used the &lt;strong&gt;same approach&lt;/strong&gt; than in the previous study.
However they normalized the expression of each gene by the average across cells of the same tumor.
Then they &lt;em&gt;winsorized&lt;/em&gt; these relative expression ([-3,3]) to limit the effect of outliers in the moving average estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here they didn’t have normals as control so &lt;strong&gt;they guessed which CNV-based cluster of cells were normal&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;consistent&lt;/em&gt; CNV patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;higher values at 1p/19q which are known losses in this cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;decoupling-genetics-lineages-and-microenvironment-in-idh-mutant-gliomas-by-scrna&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Decoupling genetics, lineages, and microenvironment in IDH-mutant gliomas by scRNA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28360267&#34;&gt;Venteicher et al. (Science 2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same lab, same idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;scRNA QC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove cells with less than 3000 expressed genes (at least one read).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove cells with average &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[log_2(\frac{TPM}{10} + 1)\]&lt;/span&gt; below 2.5 in housekeeping genes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove genes with &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[log_2(\bar{TPM}+1)\]&lt;/span&gt; below 4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the relative expression is the &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[E_r = E - \bar{E}\]&lt;/span&gt; for each gene, with &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[E=log_2(\frac{TPM}{10} + 1) \]&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To identify normal cells they first performed a hierarchical clustering of all IDH-A cells and observed three clusters.
One of the cluster is suspected to be malignant cells.
For the CNVs they used the same approach as before but corrected it with two baselines derived from the two “normal” clusters.
So again, moving average of winsorized relative expression across 100 genes.
These values were corrected with the baseline as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0 if &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[BaseMin - 0.2 &amp;lt; CNV &amp;lt; BaseMax + 0.2\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ CNV - BaseMin \]&lt;/span&gt; if &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[CNV &amp;lt; BaseMin - 0.2\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ CNV - BaseMax \]&lt;/span&gt; if &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[CNV &amp;gt; BaseMax + 0.2\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two strategies were used to classify a cell as malignant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the correlation of the gene expression profile was at least 0.3 superior when comparing with the average profile of the “malignant” cluster compared to the other two..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the “CNV signal” was higher than 0.05 and correlation with the CNVs in the “malignant” cluster was higher than 0.5.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A malignant cell was classified as malignant in both strategies or malignant in one and borderline in the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;pooling-and-deconvoluting-cells-for-normalization&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pooling and deconvoluting cells for normalization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had an idea of merging cells into meta-cells to call CNVs.
That way the higher depth allows for a much higher resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lun, Bach &amp;amp; Marioni (&lt;a href=&#34;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-016-0947-7&#34;&gt;Genome Biology 2016&lt;/a&gt;) developed a method using this strategy for normalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their objective is to avoid problems created by the high number of genes with null (or extremely low) expression.
They merge cells and compute a normalization factor for each pool.
Then these estimations are deconvoluted to get a normalization factor for each cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result of each pool is used to build a system of linear equations to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few additional tricks (e.g. how to build the pools or cluster the genes) but the main idea and tools are interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Family-based designs for gene-association studies</title>
          <link>/2017/04/09/family-based-designs-for-gene-association-studies/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/04/09/family-based-designs-for-gene-association-studies/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;Different type of family information can be used.
&lt;strong&gt;Trio designs&lt;/strong&gt; (affected offspring plus parents) seems to have the most power but having both affected and unaffected siblings is useful too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A positive result in a family-based test means there is both &lt;strong&gt;linkage&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;association&lt;/strong&gt;.
It avoids problems with population stratification or admixture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;transmission-disequilibrium-test-tdt&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transmission Disequilibrium Test (TDT)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TDT compares the number of observed allele transmitted to the affected offspring with the expected number following Mendelian transmission.
It is completely non-parametric in the sense that it doesn’t require specifying a disease model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its simple form (complete trios), the TDT is more or less a Binomial test on the number of transmitted allele according to the number of heterozygous parents.
It cannot deal with missing parents or more general pedigrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;family-based-association-tests-fbats&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Family-Based Association Tests (FBATs)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extension of the TDT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FBAT statistic represents how the observed genotype diverges from the expected genotype in individuals with phenotype:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ U = \sum T * (X-E(X|P)) \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with the sum being over all offspring and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[T=Y-\mu\]&lt;/span&gt; the centered phenotype&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[X\]&lt;/span&gt; the genotype&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(E(X|P)\) the expected genotype.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FBAT statistics is &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[\frac{U^2}{Var(U)}\]&lt;/span&gt; and follows a &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[\chi^2\]&lt;/span&gt; distribution with one degree of freedom (if at least 10 families).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The genotype &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[X\]&lt;/span&gt; can be coded to reflect the mode of inheritance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both \(E(X|P)\) and &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[Var(U)\]&lt;/span&gt; are computed under the null hypothesis from the parents/siblings genotypes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TODO empirical estimate of the variance from Lake et al 2000.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;filtering-variants&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Filtering variants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach is to focus on (homozygous) segregating variants and annotate them to assess their functional impact (frequency, location).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16619052&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Family-based designs in the age of large-scale gene-association studies.&lt;/em&gt; by Laird &amp;amp; Lange (Nature Reviews Genetics 2006)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11793685&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Family-Based Tests of Association in the Presence of Linkage.&lt;/em&gt; by Lake et al. (AJHG 200)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Epilepsy</title>
          <link>/2017/04/02/epilepsy/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/04/02/epilepsy/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;duplication-hotspots-rare-genomic-disorders-and-common-disease&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Duplication hotspots, rare genomic disorders, and common disease&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Mefford et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19477115&#34;&gt;Current Opinion in Genetics and Development 2009&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Segmental duplications sensitize ~10% of the genome&lt;/strong&gt; to recurrent microdeletions and microduplications.
Mefford et al &lt;strong&gt;review&lt;/strong&gt; the association of these &lt;strong&gt;recurrent events with diseases&lt;/strong&gt;.
A subset of these hotspots plays an important role in &lt;strong&gt;austism, schizphrenia, and epilepsy&lt;/strong&gt;.
In general, the hotspots are characterized by a &lt;strong&gt;stretch of unique sequence&lt;/strong&gt; (50 kb-10 Mb) &lt;strong&gt;flanked by large&lt;/strong&gt; (&amp;gt;10 kb), highly &lt;strong&gt;homologous&lt;/strong&gt; (&amp;gt;95%) &lt;strong&gt;segmental duplications&lt;/strong&gt;.
This context provides substrate for &lt;strong&gt;NAHR&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 15% of mental retardation syndromes seem to involve micro-deletion/duplications.
Many are non-recurrent and doesn’t involve NAHR.
However, recurrent &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; microdeletions in 17q21.31 were observed in aCGH screens, but not in controls.
This particular hotspots is interesting because an &lt;em&gt;inversion of ~900 kb&lt;/em&gt; with frequency 20% in Europeans, seem to be a &lt;em&gt;prerequisite&lt;/em&gt; for the microdeletion.
They also found other similar microdeletions in &lt;em&gt;15q24&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;16p11.2-p12.2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;10q22-q23&lt;/em&gt;.
In these studies &lt;em&gt;recurrent usually means just a few cases&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. frequencies ~1-2%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three hotspots&lt;/strong&gt; are enriched in &lt;strong&gt;multiple neuropsychiatric diseases&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;16p11.2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;1q21.1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;15q13.3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;genome-wide-copy-number-variation-in-epilepsy-novel-susceptibility-loci-in-idiopathic-generalized-and-focal-epilepsies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Genome-Wide Copy Number Variation in Epilepsy: Novel Susceptibility Loci in Idiopathic Generalized and Focal Epilepsies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Mefford et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20502679&#34;&gt;PLoS Genetics 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy has a &lt;strong&gt;prevalence ~1%&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;lifetime incidence up to 3%&lt;/strong&gt;.
Using &lt;em&gt;custom aCGH&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;517 individual&lt;/strong&gt; with mixed types of epilepsy, they found one or more &lt;strong&gt;rare genic CNVs in 8.9%&lt;/strong&gt; of them.
In addition, 2.9% of the patients carry deletions at genomic hotspots: &lt;strong&gt;15q11.2, 15q13.3 or 16p13.11&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals had idiopathic generalized epilepsy (IGE), benign epilepsy with centrotemporal spikes, and other types of idiopathic seizure disorders.
The custom aCGH had a higher probe density around 107 regions of the genome flanked by large highly homologous duplications.
The CNVs found in the 8.9% of the probands were not found in any of their 2493 controls.
The &lt;strong&gt;majority are deletions&lt;/strong&gt; (69%).
The size range from 13 kb to 15.9 Mb, with an average of 1.2 Mb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.9% of the probands had CNVs at known rearrangement hotspots.
2.9% have deletions that are either known pathogenic or significantly enriched in the epilepsy cohort.
Most of the affected probands had IGE, these CNVs actually account for 3.3% of IGE patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at non-hotspots CNVs, they found &lt;strong&gt;maximum two patients with the same gene affected&lt;/strong&gt;, most of the CNVs being unique to the proband.
Two of these genes are likely important: &lt;em&gt;CNTNAP2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;AUTS2&lt;/em&gt;.
Although, 5 individuals had 2 rare genic CNVs, it’s not clear how different they are from the rest in term of phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;rare-copy-number-variants-are-an-important-cause-of-epileptic-encephalopathies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rare copy number variants are an important cause of epileptic encephalopathies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Mefford et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22190369&#34;&gt;Annals of Neurology 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;strong&gt;315 patients&lt;/strong&gt; with EE were screened using &lt;em&gt;aCGH&lt;/em&gt;.
They found &lt;strong&gt;rare CNVs in 7.9%&lt;/strong&gt; of the patients, half of them being clearly or likely pathogenic.
Some were &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt;.
They also found some patients with CNVs in the &lt;strong&gt;known “hotspots”&lt;/strong&gt;.
Apparently their results “illuminate several novel candidates genes”, but their attempts at getting more support failed (no mutations when resequencing).
Also with this low sample size and CNV recurrence, I can’t help but wonder how many such rare CNV would be there by chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Epileptic encephalopathies&lt;/strong&gt; are the most devastating group of epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CNVs were filtered like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 probes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overlap RefSeq genes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not entirely within segmental duplication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not overlapping (&amp;gt;50%) with their 4,519 controls (=rare).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All events were also visually inspected in a genome browser.
Some rare CNVS were validated with another array.
They also did some targeted Sanger sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again &lt;strong&gt;deletions&lt;/strong&gt; in known &lt;strong&gt;epilepsy genes&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;de novo&lt;/strong&gt;, were considered &lt;strong&gt;pathogenic&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;De novo&lt;/em&gt; duplications were considered likely pathogenic, same as CNVs &amp;gt;1Mb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known epilepsy genes: &lt;em&gt;CDKL5&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;UBE3A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CNTNAP2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the discussion, they mentioned a &lt;strong&gt;significant excess of large deletions&lt;/strong&gt; in their cohort compared to controls.
2.2% of their patients have a deletion larger than 1 Mb while only 0.3% in the controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controls came from two independent studies, not using exactly the same arrays…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many gene stories fillers but nothing really convincing to support the results of their screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Context matters” gem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, our patient was also obsese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;clinical-significance-of-rare-copy-number-variations-in-epilepsy&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clinical Significance of Rare Copy Number Variations in Epilepsy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Striano et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://archneur.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?doi=10.1001/archneurol.2011.1999&#34;&gt;Archives of Neurology 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defining &lt;em&gt;rare&lt;/em&gt; CNV as not seen in DGV, they found similar number of CNVs in epilepsy patients and controls but they were significantly larger and affecting more genes.
For example CNVs larger than 1 Mb and CNVs more than 10 genes were more frequent in epilepsy patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;copy-number-variation-plays-an-important-role-in-clinical-epilepsy&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Copy number variation plays an important role in clinical epilepsy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Olson et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24811917&#34;&gt;Annals or Neurology 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a more &lt;strong&gt;clinical&lt;/strong&gt; setting, 805 patients with epilepsy were screened using aCGH arrays.
CNVs were observed in 323 patients.
The epilepsy phenotype was &lt;strong&gt;explained by a CNV&lt;/strong&gt; in at least &lt;strong&gt;5%&lt;/strong&gt; of the cases.
As usual, some CNVs located in the genomic “hotspots”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like they kept &lt;strong&gt;any CNV&lt;/strong&gt; larger than 18 kb.
They didn’t mention filtering out common CNVs or CNVs found in controls or healthy individuals.
For some patients they screened the parent to assess the mode inheritance.
They did find some &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They found overlapping CNVs in the &lt;strong&gt;Xp22.3&lt;/strong&gt; but &lt;strong&gt;without controls&lt;/strong&gt; I’m not completely convinced that it is relevant.
Moreover, looking more into this recurrent locations, there was no distinction between patients with deletion or duplication, and no evidence of epilepsy in relatives carrying the CNV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used the set of known epilepsy genes and genomic hotspots to classify CNVs as pathogenic.
They also performed a &lt;strong&gt;pathway analysis&lt;/strong&gt;, that nicely pointed at neurodevelopment, synaptic transmission, ion channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;structural-genomic-variation-in-childhood-epilepsies-with-complex-phenotypes&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Structural genomic variation in childhood epilepsies with complex phenotypes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Helbig et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24281369&#34;&gt;ELHG 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rare CNVs, sometimes &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt;, were found in patients with unclassified epilepsies and complex phenotypes.
In this study, 222 patients were screened using aCGH/SNP-array for CNVs larger than 100 kb.
88 rare CNVs in 71 patients (31.9%) were discovered.
18 of these were considered &lt;strong&gt;pathogenic&lt;/strong&gt;, and 15 &lt;strong&gt;likely pathogenic&lt;/strong&gt;.
Out of the 55 CNVs of unknown significance the &lt;strong&gt;deletion/duplication ratio was ~1:2&lt;/strong&gt;.
11 were &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; out the 42 that could be assessed, including all four variants larger than 3 Mb.
No novel recurrent CNVs larger than 100 kb were detected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patients were recruited in three centers.
One center used aCGH and the other two SNP-arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They looked for CNV:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;larger than 100 kb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overlapping a known gene.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;either:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not overlapping a benign CNV (from DGV) (=rare).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overlapping known pathogenic CNV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They classified the CNVs as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pathogenic&lt;/strong&gt; if &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; deletion or known associated with epilepsy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;likely pahotgenic&lt;/strong&gt; if &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; duplication or inherited CNVs larger than 1 Mb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;unknown significance&lt;/strong&gt; otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less interesting findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some CNVs located in known hot-spot regions (see refs) and were considered pathogenic (&lt;em&gt;so not following their previous definition…&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patients with dysmorphic features had a higher CNV burden, mostly due to CNVs of unknown significance and likely pathogenic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNVs in epilepsy: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2873910/&#34;&gt;Genome-wide copy number variation in epilepsy: novel susceptibility loci in idiopathic generalized and focal epilepsies. Mefford et al, 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNVs in epilepsy: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20398883&#34;&gt;Rare deletions at 16p13.11 predispose to a diverse spectrum of sporadic epilepsy syndromes. Heinzen et al, 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNV hotspots: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19477115&#34;&gt;Duplication hotspots, rare genomic disorders, and common disease. Mefford and Eichler, 2009&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;copy-number-variant-analysis-from-exome-data-in-349-patients-with-epileptic-encephalopathy.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Copy number variant analysis from exome data in 349 patients with epileptic encephalopathy.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Mefford et al (Epi4K consortium), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26068938&#34;&gt;Annals of Neurology, 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exome sequencing&lt;/strong&gt; of 349 trios with &lt;strong&gt;epileptic encephalopathy&lt;/strong&gt; identified &lt;strong&gt;18&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNVs in 17 patients (&lt;strong&gt;4.8%&lt;/strong&gt;).
10 of these are likely pathogenic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CNV calling was performed by &lt;strong&gt;CoNIFER pipeline&lt;/strong&gt;.
Exome-reads were mapped to exons (+- 300 bp) using mrsFAST.
30 SVD components were removed to reduce technical bias.
They also &lt;strong&gt;filtered&lt;/strong&gt; the segments called based on the number of consecutive bins and signal strength.
They &lt;strong&gt;excluded CNVs&lt;/strong&gt; with 50% or more overlapping &lt;strong&gt;repetitive or duplicated regions&lt;/strong&gt;.
CNV calls were &lt;strong&gt;manually curated&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;whatever that means…no supplementary info…only good ol’ 32 pages of tables in PDF…&lt;/em&gt;).
Finally, they filtered out CNVs observed in &lt;strong&gt;more than 1% of controls&lt;/strong&gt; (aCGH/WES).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNVs and some of the larger inherited ones were &lt;strong&gt;validated&lt;/strong&gt; by “oligonucleiotide” (&lt;em&gt;again no supplementary information&lt;/em&gt;) and SNP-array.
A &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNV was considered &lt;strong&gt;pathogenic&lt;/strong&gt; if previously associated to epilepsy or neuro-disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure about what/how they did their validation.
It seems that they first took 43 probands and tried to validate all the calls.
There, 53 of 80 (&lt;strong&gt;66%&lt;/strong&gt;) inherited CNVs and 5 of 21 (&lt;strong&gt;24%&lt;/strong&gt;) &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNVs were &lt;strong&gt;confirmed&lt;/strong&gt;.
But then they also confirmed 18 &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; in 17 patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The confirmed &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNVs ranged from 94 kb to 16 Mb, and 1 to 163 genes.
10 patients had a pathogenic &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNV.
Some &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; CNVs overlapped known &lt;strong&gt;EE genes&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;SCN1A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;SCN2A&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;GABRB3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had previously studied &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;SNV&lt;/strong&gt; in more or less the same cohort, and they compared the affected genes.
Some overlapped…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;analysis-of-rare-copy-number-variation-in-absence-epilepsies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis of rare copy number variation in absence epilepsies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Addis et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27123475&#34;&gt;Neurology Genetics 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They looked at CNVs in &lt;strong&gt;144 children&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;absence epilepsy&lt;/strong&gt; using SNP-arrays.
&lt;strong&gt;11%&lt;/strong&gt; of the patients had a &lt;strong&gt;rare CNVs&lt;/strong&gt; that disrupt genes associated with neuronal development and function.
They also found some patients with CNVs in the &lt;strong&gt;known “hotspots”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They selected CNVs following those criteria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;gt;12 supporting probes and &amp;gt;20 kb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not overlapping (&amp;gt;90%) DGV CNVs with frequency &amp;gt; 0.1% (=rare).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNV overlapping at least one exon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;pathogenicity&lt;/strong&gt; was based on the gene content, size, frequency and overlap with relevant genes (epilepsy and other neuro-diseases).
They don’t detail their criteria more…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CNVs were validated by real-time quantitative PCR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, &lt;strong&gt;cell adhesion&lt;/strong&gt; is a mechanism that is thought to contribute to epileptogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cenet&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CENet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://biotechnologyfocus.ca/public-private-partnership-to-seek-personalized-treatment-approach-for-drug-resistant-epilepsy/&#34;&gt;Information gathered here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personalized Medicine in the Treatment of Epilepsy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify variants&lt;/strong&gt; that predispose for &lt;strong&gt;epilepsy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify variants&lt;/strong&gt; that predicts &lt;strong&gt;drug response&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 anti-epileptic drugs, effective in ~70% of patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ID associated with higher resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ID in 25% of the patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Particularly problematic in children.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is to identify genetic changes that predispose people to epilepsy and changes that predict response to different anti-epileptic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there are over 20 different anti-epileptic drugs available today, these drugs are ineffective in about one third of patients. Epilepsy is particularly problematic in children since uncontrolled seizures in the developing brain largely contribute to cognitive decline. Managing epilepsy associated with intellectual disability is especially challenging since these symptoms are associated with a high rate of resistance to anti-epileptic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ASHG 2014 abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy is a common complex neurological disorder characterized by recurrent episodes of paroxysmal abnormal electrical discharges in the brain (seizure). In 65% of epileptic individuals seizures occur without detectable lesion in the brain. Intellectual disability (ID) is observed in ~25% of epileptic individuals. Although treatment is effective in the majority of cases, more than 30% of patients are resistant to anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs). In this project, we hypothesize that pharmaco-resistant epilepsies (PRE) have different etiologies than other epilepsy syndromes associated with the same clinical manifestations, and posit that genetic factors can be used to predict response to AEDs. In 2013, we united Canadian clinicians and investigators to create the Canadian Epilepsy Network (CENet). In order to identify highly penetrant genetic variants that can predict resistance to AEDs, we will conduct whole genome sequencing (WGS) on 1000 epileptic individuals with extremes of response to AED treatment, including 200 multiplex families, as well as 200 epileptic trios (patient + both parents) with severe epilepsy and ID. Based on our previous studies in patients with ID or autism spectrum disorders, we expect a high rate of de novo mutation for epilepsies associated with these co-morbidities. Potentially causative genes/variants will be validated in additional epilepsy samples available through our large collaborative network with similar but complementary projects in the US (Epi4K - 4,000 epilepsy genomes) and Europe (EpiPGX). We will also assess the clinical utility of whole genome sequencing as a diagnostic test for epilepsy in a prospective cohort of 600 epileptic individuals. So far, pre-screening of 36 known genes for epileptic encephalopathy (EE) in 95 patients led us to identify 11 causative mutations in total (11.6%). At the end of the project, we expect to identify 50 novel genes causing severe forms of epilepsy and PRE. Using this catalog of gene variants, we will develop and validate a diagnostic resource (PRE-GENE) to implement WGS as the gold-standard diagnostic test for PRE in clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;animal-models-of-epilepsy&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Animal Models of Epilepsy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Kandratovicius et al. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4164293/&#34;&gt;Neuropsychaitric Dis Treat. 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some models replicate &lt;strong&gt;symptomatic epilepsies&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e. where the epilepsy is a symptom of an underlying problem, such as an injury, an infection, a congenital brain malformation, a tumour, or a metabolic disorder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few other are genetic models of absence seizure but the genetic part is more used for convenience than for investigating the genetic factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epilepsy Vs Chronic epilepsy. Are chronic just more recurrent ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chemoconvulsant&lt;/strong&gt; used on mice models to induce chronic epilepsy. Expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrical stimulation&lt;/strong&gt; are useful to study brain damage and after effects but are not cell specific and also expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kindling seems to be another form of electrical stimulation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Young mice can also be exposed to 30 min of &lt;strong&gt;hot air&lt;/strong&gt; (40C) which leads to convulsions. Same with &lt;strong&gt;hypoxia&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fluid Percussion Injury is a machine to induce &lt;strong&gt;physical brain trauma&lt;/strong&gt; to mice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audiogenic rats where acoustic stimulation triggers seizure. Useful but not really a genetic model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monogenic mouse&lt;/strong&gt; models of abscence epilepsy. Some &lt;strong&gt;rat&lt;/strong&gt; models are polygenic and more realistic (e.g. responding to drugs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They also mention &lt;em&gt;lethargic, tottering, leaner, and stargazer&lt;/em&gt; mouse models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;epilepsygene-resource&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;EpilepsyGene resource&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC4384015&#34;&gt;Ran et al (NAR 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyzed more than 1000 publications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contains information for &lt;strong&gt;499 genes amd 3931 variants&lt;/strong&gt; (mostly SNVs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Variants annotated and scored by the number of tools predicting a &lt;strong&gt;deleterious effect&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;154 high-confidence genes&lt;/em&gt; with score &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[\ge10\]&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Four co-expression modules from BrainSpan (RNA-seq of brain development).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Microsatellite Instability</title>
          <link>/2017/02/05/microsatellite-instability/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/02/05/microsatellite-instability/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;Microsatellites are a type of STRs with repeat units of 1-6 bp.
Microsatellite instability is an indicator of larger genome instability and an important prognostic factor in several cancers (e.g. colorectal).
MSI is actually a marker of favorable prognosis.
It’s a form of hypermutation caused by defective DNA mismatch repair (MMR).
For example, through inactivation of &lt;em&gt;MLH1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;MSH2&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;MSH3&lt;/em&gt; genes.
For this reason, MSI is also characterized by high rates of single-nucleotide-substitution (SNS) mutations.
Usually, electrophoresis is used to estimate the size of five to 7 MS markers in tumor/normal design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mononucleotides repeats are believed to be the most sensitive and specific for detecting MSI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few methods that try to detect MSI from sequencing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;msisensor&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MSIsensor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/bioinformatics/btt755&#34;&gt;Niu et al. (Bioinformatics 2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MSIsensor estimated the length distribution of MS sites in both normal and tumor and test for significant differences.
The workflow is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan the reference for homopolymers of minimum total length of 5 bp and maximum unit length of 5 bp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract all the reads around these sites (+/- 2 Kbp).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Count reads with khmer supporting every possible repeat length.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each site is tested for a difference in these khmer read counts between normal/tumor (with multiple-test correction).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this I assume they can only analyze accurately MS shorter than the repeat length.
The advantage compared to STR detection method is that it skips the actual genotyping steps and directly compare the normal/tumor.
This is both clever and ease the downstream analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They test their approach with exome data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++ program available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ding-lab/msisensor&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;pipd-in-rna-seq&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PI/PD in RNA-seq&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0063056&#34;&gt;Lu et al. (PLOS One 2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their approach relies on indels in MS in genes expressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract or create MS annotation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detect indels with DINDEL .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filter out dbSNP entries and select indels in MS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the proportion of MS insertion over insertions (PI) and same for deletions (PD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the MSI-seq as PI/PD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focusing on coding sequences, they found significant differences between MSI samples and Hapmap, but not between MSS samples and Hapmap.
Deletions are also slightly smaller in MSI than the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then they show that their MSI-seq estimate nicely discriminates between MSI ans MSS samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They is no tool to automatically run the protocol but it should be easy to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;msings&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;mSINGS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://clinchem.aaccjnls.org/content/60/9/1192.long&#34;&gt;Salipante et al. (Clinical Chemistry 2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indels called with VarScan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identification of MS marker loci that show length variation in known MSI samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute a baseline for each site using control samples (MSI-negative).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute mean and SD of the number of alleles (with at least 5% of reads) in each locus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If more than (mean+3xSD) the locus is classified &lt;em&gt;unstable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If more than 20% of the markers are &lt;em&gt;unstable&lt;/em&gt; the sample is concluded MSI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They tested their approach on exome data and targeted gene panel sequencing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The MS markers are available in the supplement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix of bash and python available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/uwlabmed/msings&#34;&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not very convincing. E.g. Figures without axis legends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gem about using a the mean + 3 SD threshold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This metric provides a statistical framework for evaluating the stability or instability of any particular marker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;msiseq&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MSIseq&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/articles/srep13321&#34;&gt;Huang et al. (Scientific Reports 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MSIseq takes a machine learning approach to classify a sample as MSI or MSS from the SNV/indel variant calls.
The inputs for the model were mutation rates for SNVs or indels, in or outside annotated STRs and the cancer type.
They tried logistic regression, decision tree, random forest and naive bayes.
The four approaches gave very good accuracy (~98%) with experimental MSS/MSI classification.
Interestingly the decision tree used only one predictor, the number of indels in annotated repeats.
This means that we could simply use one threshold on this indel rate and be fine (i.e. no need for a fancy machine learning approach).
Meaning that we could summarize their R package by &lt;code&gt;ifelse(indelRateSTR &amp;gt; 0.395, &#34;MSI&#34;, &#34;MSS&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;.
Actually their package also implement the training of the machine learning, which could be very useful if only specific regions are accessible (targeted sequencing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The R package is available through &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/MSIseq/index.html&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;msiplus&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MSIplus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jmd.amjpathol.org/article/S1525-1578(15)00153-1/fulltext&#34;&gt;Hempelmann et al. (Journal of Molecular Diagnostics 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MSIplus simultaneously detects MSI and variants in mutational hotspots of colorectal cancers (KRAS, NRAS, BRAF).
They use amplicon sequencing to ensure high sequencing coverage at the loci of interest, or for a cost-effective way to test many samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VarScan to detect SNVs and indels, mSINGS to determine MSI status.
They use a set of blood samples as baseline for mSINGS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because they use existing bioinfo tools, the value of this works lies in the loci and their amplification before sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;to-go-further&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To go further&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read on how MSI is a marker of favorable prognosis.
For example from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23235802?dopt=Abstract&amp;amp;holding=npg&#34;&gt;this study&lt;/a&gt; and references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>The Self-Assessment Trap</title>
          <link>/2017/01/14/the-self-assessment-trap/</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/01/14/the-self-assessment-trap/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;p&gt;I just read a short correspondence about the self-assessment trap, i.e. when &lt;strong&gt;the author is the judge, jury and executioner&lt;/strong&gt; of comparing his method against existing methods.
One visible outcome is that most methods are found to be the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt;, which is unlikely to be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical explanation for this bias is the selection by the authors of just the metrics in which their method is better.
Different aspects of the same problem are emphasized in different papers and used for benchmarking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is difficult to benchmark methods, especially in biological sciences.
The data is too small, or the expectation is not completely clear, or the experimental validation is partial or too unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They propose a few guidelines to avoid this trap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use third-party validation and previously unseen data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use more than one metric to evaluate the methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Report good methods even if not the best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress the impartial assessment to editors/reviewers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change scientific culture to value follow-up studies to confirm/refute results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then mention some initiatives (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.the-dream-project.org&#34;&gt;DREAM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://predictioncenter.org/&#34;&gt;CASP&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebi.ac.uk/msd-srv/capri/&#34;&gt;CAPRI&lt;/a&gt;) that address at least the first 3-4 guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=PMC3261704&#34;&gt;The self-assessment trap: can we all be better than average? by Norel et al.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Lit Digest - SVs and TEs</title>
          <link>/2017/01/10/lit-digest-svs-and-tes/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2017/01/10/lit-digest-svs-and-tes/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;crowdvariant-a-crowdsourcing-approach-to-classify-copy-number-variants&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CrowdVariant: a crowdsourcing approach to classify copy number variants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/12/13/093526&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no good gold-standard dataset for small CNVs (&amp;lt;10 kb).
CrowdVariant is a crowdsourcing framework that aim at identifying high quality CNV calls in NA24385, an Ashkenazim reference sample from Genome In A Bottle Consortium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They show that even annotations from non-expert helps assigning copy number status from putative calls.
They then provide 1 781 of such high confidence CNVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They only analyze deletions but they have Illumina data for the trio and 10X genomics for the son. With 10X they can separate the haplotype (How exactly ?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A user is shown IGV images of the region, but have no information about which region it is, which technology or the weight of their decision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some non-experts didn’t do it well or didn’t understand but most of the others could accurately distinguish CN0, CN1 or CN2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/svviz/svviz&#34;&gt;svviz&lt;/a&gt; is a semi-automated visualization tool to look a read mapping around SV breakpoints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;new-sv-detection-method-devro&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New SV detection method: DevRO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/12/15/094474&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DevRO uses short insert paired-end reads and long-range mate-pairs.
It uses PEM and read depth.
It analyzes multiple samples/populations without the need for pairwise comparisons (like the aCGH-adapted caller).
It also detects deletions in the reference assembly (novel insertion I guess).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like they first count discordant mapping in 1 kb bins in each population.
Then they retrieve the bins whose fraction of discordant are different between populations and test them better.
I’m not sure about the rest of the method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In their analysis, they compared two populations (of 2 individuals) of rabbits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At first glance, the manuscript (text and figures) does not look convincing and there is no link to a software page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;References: SVDetect (Zeitouni et al., 2010)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;detecting-large-repeat-exansion-with-expansionhunter&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Detecting large repeat exansion with ExpansionHunter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/12/19/093831&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recently discovered hexamer (GGCCCC) repeat expansion in the C9orf72 locus is a major cause of both ALS and frontotemporal dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat expansion are tricky to assess.
Repeat-primed PCR with fragment length analysis is widely used but challenging to interpret, especially when indels are present.
And they don’t give an estimate of the length of the expansion.
Southern blotting is the gold standard to estimate repeat length but can be challenging to set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method uses the “in-repeat” reads to estimate the length of large repeat expansion.
The challenges are finding these IRRs, making sure the mapping is good and estimating the length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PCR-free WGS (45x) of two ALS (amyotrophic lateral sclerosis) cohorts for a total of 3 001 samples !!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a C++ program (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Illumina/ExpansionHunter&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;detecting-te-insertion-from-wgs-data-with-mcclintock-pipeline&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Detecting TE insertion from WGS data with McClintock pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/12/19/095372&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary goal of the McClintock pipeline is to lower the barrier to installation, use, and evaluation of multiple WGS-based TE detection methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impressive list of existing TE detection method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ngs_te_mapper&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;TE-locate&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;PoPoolationTE&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;RetroSeq&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;RelocaTE&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;TEMP&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was developped for yeast but seems to have in mind all the other organisms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://msb.embopress.org/content/7/1/537&#34;&gt;Self-assessment trap: Can we all be better than average ?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;experimental-evolution-reveals-hyperparasitic-interactions-among-transposable-elements&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experimental evolution reveals hyperparasitic interactions among transposable elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org/content/113/51/14763.short&#34;&gt;PNAS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems like they experimentally reproduced the “selfish” evolution of TE using &lt;em&gt;mariner&lt;/em&gt; TE in flies.
They observed the known selfish properties, even within families where some non-autonomous members hijack autonomous ones (hyperparasitism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;detecting-dna-methylation-in-alu-elements&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Detecting DNA methylation in &lt;em&gt;Alu&lt;/em&gt; elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://genome.cshlp.org/content/27/1/118.abstract&#34;&gt;Genome Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cancer cells exhibits widespread hypomethylation affecting large chromosomal domains.
NSUMA (Next-generation Sequencing of UnMethylated Alu) is a new sequencing approach that enrich for unmethylated &lt;em&gt;Alu&lt;/em&gt; and a flanking nonrepetitive sequence.
It detects 10 times more unmethylated &lt;em&gt;Alu&lt;/em&gt; in cancer cells compared to normal cells.
Still, &lt;em&gt;Alu&lt;/em&gt; are less hypomethylated than other TEs.
They conclude that &lt;em&gt;Alu&lt;/em&gt; elements contribute to the epigenetic changes but how do they know it originated from the &lt;em&gt;Alu&lt;/em&gt; ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alu hypomethylation is associated with higher chromosomal instability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;detecting-complex-sv-in-cancer-using-cougar&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Detecting complex SV in cancer using CouGaR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://genome.cshlp.org/content/27/1/107.abstract&#34;&gt;Genome Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CouGaR uses both read depth and discordant mapping.
It identifies amplified regions across chromosomes and link them using the discordant mapping.
Then the network-like problem is resolved by estimating the contigs and copy number estimates.
See the nice figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They validated 15 out of 17 predicted fusion in pediatric gliomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They surveyed complex SVs across samples from TCGA.
They selected 467 samples that are most likely harboring CGRs.
Then I don’t understand why they are surprised to see more contigs than in previous studies.
They explain it might be the lack of method or small sample size while it’s maybe their specific selection for CGRs…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CouGaR identified the occurrence of ‘chromoplexy’ in nearly 63% of all prostate cancer samples and 30% of all bladder cancer samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently chromoplexy is a complex SV event involving many different chromosomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A stand-alone visualization tool is also available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other similar methods: BAMBAM and nFuse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Local assembly</title>
          <link>/2016/08/17/local-assembly/</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2016/08/17/local-assembly/</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;tigra-a-targeted-iterative-graph-routing-assembler-for-breakpoint-assembly&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TIGRA: A targeted iterative graph routing assembler for breakpoint assembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Ken Chen et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24307552&#34;&gt;Genome Research 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Targeted Iterative Graph Routing Assembler&lt;/em&gt; was widely used in large-scale projects (e.g. 1KGP) for &lt;strong&gt;breakpoints assembly of deletions and mobile element insertion&lt;/strong&gt;.
It’s an old effort, that they started in 2008, which was optimized and improved across the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify, TIGRA assembles the breakpoint region of SV, &lt;strong&gt;not the entire SV region&lt;/strong&gt;.
Another clarification: TIGRA is used to &lt;strong&gt;validate existing calls&lt;/strong&gt; and reduce the FDR, not so much to characterize SV mechanism or features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reads are extracted&lt;/strong&gt; around the predicted breakpoint (+- 500bp-1Kbp).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mapped reads &lt;em&gt;and their mate&lt;/em&gt; are retrieved from the BAM files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If multiple samples are available and their genotype is known, reads from the variant-containing samples can be pooled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reads are &lt;strong&gt;assembled&lt;/strong&gt; using a de Bruijn graph.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple k-mer sizes are &lt;em&gt;iteratively&lt;/em&gt; used (starting from small k-mers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously assembled contigs taken as &lt;em&gt;pseudo-reads&lt;/em&gt; in the next iterations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tips, likely created by sequencing errors, are pruned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bubbles are joined when the size difference is lower than 3 nucleotides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entire reads&lt;/em&gt; are used to distinguish repeats, instead of k-mers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assembled sequences are &lt;strong&gt;mapped back to the reference genome&lt;/strong&gt; using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phrap.org/phredphrapconsed.html&#34;&gt;cross_match&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every contig is tested although they don’t explain explicitly how these contigs are retrieved from the graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contigs with more than two hits or substitution rate higher than 0.5% (low isn’t it ?) are not reported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;glocal&lt;/em&gt; alignment is used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They tested TIGRA assembly step against Velvet, SGA, Phrap and SPAdes.
They used datasets with known deletions breakpoints and mobile element insertions.
TIGRA shows the &lt;em&gt;highest proportion of validated SVs&lt;/em&gt; in any situations.
The validation rates are lower than I thought (40%-80%) but it might reflect the low sequencing depth.
They also managed to detect quasi-full length Alu insertion (Was it because they knew it was there ?).
TIGRA is more robust to low-coverage alleles than other existing methods, thanks to its multiple k-mer size process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems mainly &lt;strong&gt;focused on deletions, duplication (not benchmarked) and mobile insertion&lt;/strong&gt;, although they mention being able to detect any type of de novo SV and having specific strategies to deal with inversion or reciprocal translocations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it handles repeats slightly better than other methods, by using full reads instead of k-mers, repeated sequences longer than the read length will not be resolved and are bound to create ambiguous graphs.
Indeed they observed a reduction of assembled breakpoints with higher breakpoint homology.
It is implemented to assemble small breakpoint regions, hence &lt;strong&gt;require almost nucleotide resolution as input&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They mention an important drop in validation rate for RD-based regions. Is it because of the input breakpoints being less precise ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn’t understand how they define their contigs (used in the iterative process; aligned against the reference). Is it all possible paths in the graph ? Only unambiguous paths ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TIGRA is available here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.mdanderson.org/main/TIGRA&#34;&gt;http://bioinformatics.mdanderson.org/main/TIGRA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;breakpoint-profiling-of-64-cancer-genomes-reveals-numerous-complex-rearrangements-spawned-by-homology-independent-mechanisms.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Breakpoint profiling of 64 cancer genomes reveals numerous complex rearrangements spawned by homology-independent mechanisms.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Malhotra et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3638133&amp;amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;amp;rendertype=abstract&#34;&gt;Genome Research 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, they looked at 64 genomes from 7 different cancers and tried to characterize the breakpoints of somatic SVs.
Here, I’ll focus on the local assembly part of the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They &lt;strong&gt;modified SGA assembler&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3290790/&#34;&gt;Simpson and Durbin 2012&lt;/a&gt;) to &lt;strong&gt;report all paths&lt;/strong&gt; from all connected components from the string graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extracted read pairs around the breakpoint (+- 500 bp).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assembly: &lt;em&gt;sga preprocess&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sga index&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sga correct&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sga index&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sga rmdup&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sga overlap&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sga assemble&lt;/em&gt;, modified &lt;em&gt;sga walk&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contig aligned on reference using BWA-SW.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split-mapping with &amp;gt;25bp non-overlap with adjacent mapping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comparison with original SV signature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistent with TIGRA benchmark, they estimate their validation rate around 80% for deletion.
They mention that deletion are the easiest to validate and expect lower overall validation rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does this perform in regions with repeats ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does it scale up when assembling larger regions ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;discovery-and-characterization-of-alu-repeat-sequences-via-precise-local-read-assembly&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discovery and characterization of Alu repeat sequences via precise local read assembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Wildschutte et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26503250&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Res.&lt;/em&gt; 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Kidd’s group built on existing approaches to &lt;strong&gt;detect Alu insertion&lt;/strong&gt; and attempted to &lt;strong&gt;assemble the full allelic sequence&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retro-Seq selected &lt;strong&gt;insertion-supporting reads&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One pair mapped uniquely, the other in Alu consensus or instance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum of 2 supporting reads per call.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call &lt;em&gt;within 500 bp of existing Alu were removed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reads for each insertion were &lt;strong&gt;assembled with CAP3&lt;/strong&gt; (overlap-layout-consensus).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read pair within 200 bp and with soft-clip &amp;gt; 20 bp were added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CAP3 uses read-pair information and links contigs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They keep sequence with at least 30 bp of Alu and 30 bp of non-gapped sequence..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breakpoint determination&lt;/strong&gt; using a suite of (old) programs.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orientation guessed by a &lt;em&gt;BLAT&lt;/em&gt; on the reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Candidate breakpoints from &lt;em&gt;miropeats&lt;/em&gt; (semi-automated graphical alignment).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global alignment of the insertion breakpoints using &lt;em&gt;stretcher&lt;/em&gt; (to see TSD).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of &lt;em&gt;manual review/curation&lt;/em&gt; in the end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pipeline available on GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/KiddLab/insertion-assembly&#34;&gt;https://github.com/KiddLab/insertion-assembly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;enhanced-structural-variant-and-breakpoint-detection-using-svmerge-by-integration-of-multiple-detection-methods-and-local-assembly.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enhanced structural variant and breakpoint detection using SVMerge by integration of multiple detection methods and local assembly.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Wong et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3046488%7B&amp;amp;%7Dtool=pmcentrez%7B&amp;amp;%7Drendertype=abstract&#34;&gt;Genome Biology 2010&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SVMerge is a pipeline that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes SV prediction with a collection of callers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filter them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merge them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validate them using local assembly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the assembly step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reads around the breakpoint are extracted (+- 1-2 kbp).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mapped read and mate pair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reads were written in FASTA with interleaved read pairs (Velvet input?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV discarded if too many reads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assembly using ABySS or Velvet.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With and without scaffolding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All contigs were considered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contig alignment using Exonerate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignment parsing.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To verify the breakpoint location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To verify read depth change (het deletions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perl scripts available here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://svmerge.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;http://svmerge.sourceforge.net/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-sv-assembler-to-check&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other SV-assembler to check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;laSV: &lt;a href=&#34;http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/doi/10.1093/nar/gkv831&#34;&gt;Local sequence assembly reveals a high-resolution profile of somatic structural variations in 97 cancer genomes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AsmVar: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gigasciencejournal.com/content/4/1/64&#34;&gt;Discovery, genotyping and characterization of structural variation and novel sequence at single nucleotide resolution from de novo genome assemblies on a population scale&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CREST: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3527068&amp;amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;amp;rendertype=abstract&#34;&gt;CREST maps somatic structural variation in cancer genomes with base-pair resolution. Wang et al. Nat Methods. 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SV-STAT: &lt;a href=&#34;http://scfbm.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13029-016-0051-0&#34;&gt;SV-STAT accurately detects structural variation via alignment to reference-based assemblies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PopIns: &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/doi/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv273&#34;&gt;PopIns: population-scale detection of novel sequence insertions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>SV, gene expression, cancer types, Alu insertions.</title>
          <link>/2016/06/18/sv-gene-expression-cancer-types-alu-insertions./</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jean Monlong</author>
          <guid>/2016/06/18/sv-gene-expression-cancer-types-alu-insertions./</guid>
          <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;the-impact-of-structural-variation-on-human-gene-expression&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The impact of structural variation on human gene expression&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Chiang et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/06/09/055962?rss=1%2522&#34;&gt;biorXiv 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group from Ira Hall and the GTEx consortium investigated how much SVs affect gene expression and put it in context with existing SNV eQTLs work.
The jointly analyze the effect of SNVs, indels and SVs across 13 tissues in 147 individuals.
Their main results are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SVs look like the causal variants of &lt;strong&gt;3.3-7% of eQTLs&lt;/strong&gt;. Much more than predicted before and a large enrichment considering their genomic scarcity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;88%&lt;/strong&gt; of the putative causal SVs are &lt;strong&gt;non-coding&lt;/strong&gt;, but enriched in enhancer and regulatory regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;49 SVs are predicted to be causal of known GWAS hits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30% of common SV-eQTLs&lt;/strong&gt; are &lt;strong&gt;not well tagged&lt;/strong&gt; by flanking SNPs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;classification-of-cancers-based-on-copy-number-variation-landscapes&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Classification of cancers based on copy number variation landscapes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Zhang et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27266344?dopt=Abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;BBA&lt;/em&gt; 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They built a classifier taking as input CNVs of 23K genes and &lt;strong&gt;classifying six cancer types&lt;/strong&gt;.
They reached &lt;strong&gt;0.75 accuracy with only 19 genes&lt;/strong&gt;.
For classification, they used the Dagging algorithm, which chunks the data and feed them to a base classifier.
Then the consensus over the chunks is used as final classification.
The accuracy represents the proportion correctly classified samples.
In figure 1 we see how the accuracy increases rapidly with the number of features to then plateau around 75%.
Some cancer types are more accurately classified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 19 genes are: RPS15, IL17RC, CUL2, SMPD3, MIR4703, CDKN2A, RFFL, CTBP2, MMD2, SEMA6A, ZFPM1, CDC25A, ZMYND11, KBTBD6, CELF5, EGFR, PIGL, ZNF503-AS1, RBFOX1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction has some interesting sentences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One study based on SNP microarray data from 2500 individuals with no known disease showed that a CNV that is at least 100 kb is approximately harbored by 65% to 80% of individuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] copy number variants (CNV) that could alter the diploid status of particular locus of the genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn’t know about the &lt;strong&gt;relation between stress and CNV&lt;/strong&gt;.
Under stress (e.g. hypoxia) repair of broken replication may switch from homologous recombination to non-homologous repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;further-readings&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Further readings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the introduction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.annualreviews.org.proxy3.library.mcgill.ca/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev-genet-102209-163544&#34;&gt;Human Copy Number Variation and Complex Genetic Disease&lt;/a&gt; (review from E. Eichler).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19166990&#34;&gt;Population Analysis of Large Copy Number Variants and Hotspots of Human Genetic Disease&lt;/a&gt; (SNP-array across 2500 healthy individuals).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;discovery-and-characterization-of-alu-repeat-sequences-via-precise-local-read-assembly&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discovery and characterization of Alu repeat sequences via precise local read assembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Wildschutte et al, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26503250&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Res.&lt;/em&gt; 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Kidd’s group built on existing approaches to &lt;strong&gt;detect Alu insertion&lt;/strong&gt; and attempted to &lt;strong&gt;assemble the full allelic sequence&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;ME-insertion supporting reads&lt;/em&gt; are assembled using a classic &lt;em&gt;overlap-layout-consensus&lt;/em&gt; strategy.
&lt;strong&gt;Low-coverage WGS&lt;/strong&gt; from 53 samples (Human Genome Diversity Project) was &lt;strong&gt;pooled&lt;/strong&gt;.
They also devised a &lt;em&gt;genotyping experiment&lt;/em&gt; of their assembled insertion and validated through PCR.
Briefly, reads are remapped to both the reference and mutated region and mapping used to estimate genotype likelihoods.
With their assembled sequences they could &lt;em&gt;observe and quantify&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;premature insertion&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;5’ truncation&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Some&lt;/strong&gt; variable Alu seem to arise &lt;strong&gt;from non-retrotransposition mechanisms&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;strong&gt;challenge&lt;/strong&gt; with short-read data seems to be &lt;strong&gt;colocation of reference and non-reference repeats&lt;/strong&gt;.
For example, prediction within 500 bp were removed in this study.
Later they estimate from simulation that they might miss half of the insertions because of this criteria, consistent with the number from Chaisson et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Breakpoint determination seems tricky&lt;/em&gt;.
They had to use a series of (old) programs to align, orient, realign the assembled sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used &lt;em&gt;PacBio from CHM1 to validate the assembly&lt;/em&gt;.
In fact they ran their analysis on short-read data for the haploid cell line.
It’s not exactly the same as their pooled analysis but the best they could do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AluY subfamilies is still mobile, especially AluYa5 and AluYb8.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active Alus contains a RNA Pol III promoter that mobilizes L1 machinery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Same as L1, inserted Alu are flanked by target site duplication and a poly-A tail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They cite a few modern methods that uses split-read, soft-clipped and unmapped reads to detect repeat insertion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23233656&#34;&gt;RetroSeq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23921633&#34;&gt;alu-detect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22745252&#34;&gt;Tea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25348035&#34;&gt;Mobster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
